He will be a staff for the righteous, with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
in our time.
many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to see and to know reality
as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate
everyday life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen
Damick and Father Stephen De Young host this live Colin show, focused on enchantment in creation,
The union of the scene and unseen as made by God
experienced by mankind throughout history. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Greetings, giant killers, dragon slayers. You are listening to the 128th episode of the Lord of
Spirits podcast. Some say it's gone on too long. Nevertheless, I'm Father
Andrew Stephen Damick and with me is the only ancient faith radio
podcaster ever to have been featured as a photograph on the wall of multiple
restaurants in Northeastern Pennsylvania, Father Steve India.
and we're not live.
This is our annual.
You can still call in though.
You just see what happens.
You always invite people to do that,
but I'm not sure that anyone has bothered it.
Yeah.
Well, how would we know?
How would we know?
It's right.
The phone's just ringing ring and nothing happens.
Yeah, especially this is gonna be Thanksgiving.
I don't think anybody's gonna be sitting around.
Yeah.
Are you gonna do that to somebody
as one of the higher ups of Ancient Face?
Are you gonna make some poor sap?
Like just sit in the studio.
I mean, there is some,
There is someone we can do that.
two. None other than the great Mike Turduck-Anne D'Againn, who's not going to be taking your
calls probably. Unless I send him off to do that, I bet he obediently would do it too. Maybe
I should try. That's just that. But this is our annual Thanksgiving pre-record following
in the footsteps of the great Giants episode in 2020. Last time, we talked about myth
And it turns out that there is a hunger among our listeners for the lurid
details. Laura details. Yeah, we do mean lured. Yeah, it's not a joke this time.
Laura details of ancient mystery cults. So during this pre-recorded episode, we're going to be
ruining everyone's Thanksgiving dinner by talking about mystery cults in general along
with some specifics. And to strike a very serious note, this is a parental advisory, everybody. So
So we recommend listening to this one yourself before you let any minor
listen to this because it turns out that ancient mystery cults are gross in a lot of really
disturbing ways. But also you also could just man up and just straight up be like, hey
relatives who I'd ever see who are here for Thanksgiving, listen to this great podcast I love
and play that this is their introduction. And the great thing is it'll be airing at 7pm
Eastern 4pm Pacific so like it could just ripple across the country depending on when you guys eat
Thanksgiving dinner.
So well, it wouldn't actually ripple across the country father and her because the way time zones work is that
4 p.m. Pacific and
7 p.m. Eastern are the same time. That's what I'm saying is it it well ripple it's gonna be playing simultaneously across all four time zones
That's true. I guess but there is a slide. I think there's a three-second delay so
so for all of them I think so
Yes, so it's so that that isn't affected either. Yeah
You're not having a good day so far, brother.
I know.
I mean, the truth is, is the people in California
do hear it actually slightly later than those
who are in Ohio because it does take longer
to get through the wires, but not a lot longer.
There you go, the tubes.
So yeah, we are talking about mystery cults.
There are some lurid details,
but we're not talking about them for the lurid details.
talking about them because
This is actually a significant piece of the context of the ancient religious world.
And also it turns out that there are some specific tie-ins with the Bible, with Christianity,
as always, with this show.
But you know, typically you're going to have to wait to get those until the very, very end.
But we are, unlike as is our normal want, we're actually going to start by talking about
mystery cults in the first half, right?
Yes, we are actually going to be talking about mystery cults.
So...
not their relationship to Christianity, but mystery cults as such, right here at the beginning.
Right, so the question I...
We'll begin at the beginning, a very good place to start.
That's right.
So this question we should begin with though is, so what exactly is a cult?
I think that when we talk about mystery cults, probably people, they just immediately kind of
impose the modern idea of that word cult.
Yes.
Well, even modern idea, modern idea and popular idea are not identical.
Yeah, it turns out that
I think that when most people say they were caught,
what they mean is a religion that I think is weird
and maybe especially has some kind of care.
Or maybe is weird.
Yeah, right.
Well, I mean, martial apple white
was a little bit of a weird dude, just objectively.
I mean, people call us a cult
and what they mean by that is I find orthodox Christianity weird.
But they're wrong.
It's not weird.
It's deep.
That I'm right about martial apple white.
normally normal.
But also...
So there's, I think it's probably useful to note that if you've ever studied and most
people haven't because why would you, if you've ever studied sociology of religion,
sociology of religion will def, they have four words that they use to define religious
groups, church, denomination, sect, and cult, and there's two criteria by which they judge
this. There's the criterion of what is the relationship of the group to the wider society
is it good or bad? Does the group see itself as exclusively true?
or not, and sociology of religion defines a cult
as a group that has a bad relationship
with the wider society, but doesn't see itself
as exclusively true.
So that might be useful to you in some contexts,
but again, it's not what we're talking about here.
But that deviates from sort of the common usage
in that a lot of things like heaven's gate,
a cult that I was just bringing up
for the branch to videons or...
Right.
whomever
would make claims of exclusivity.
Yes, yes.
In the sociological context, they would use the word
sect to refer to those exclusive groups.
But we commonly, yeah, be all just weird, right?
There are certain, again, non-professional,
in the sense that cult is in cult of personality,
like Mussolini or Gandhi.
Anyway, where...
I didn't think we'd have a living.
Yeah, the reference right here, this early in the, here we are.
The, you have the, I wasn't a CM Punk reference.
See, people don't even know now.
The, the idea that you have some leader,
like a cult leader, right.
And that's often a huge factor of the popular usage is that there is some guy who
everybody's following.
Yeah, and there's part of what makes it cult controlling aspect often.
Yes, cutting people off from the outside world being insurred.
Right. You know, so okay.
Now if you find all cults, as we said before, inevitably become sex cults.
And that usage of the word true.
And it turns out that that's also true about a lot of what we're going to be discussing.
Hence the parental advisory everybody.
If you come across the word cult in a book,
You know.
like an scholarly book or a religious book, a theological book, a history book, it's
not going to be used that way.
So it's actually much more kind of neutral without the sort of judgy, judgyness that comes
with a popular usage.
It just generally means a worshiping community, a cult.
So in many cases, cult is essentially a synonym for a religion, but also can be used particularly
in the Christian context, Christian.
scholarly context to refer to the veneration of a saint. So they could say, well, the cult
of Saint Paul was very, was very popular in this region.
The cult of the martyrs. Yeah, exactly. And all they mean by that is, you know, veneration,
religious veneration, right? So it's very, very different sense of it.
It's also sometimes used to refer to someone anachronistically, as we've said before
the show, refer to the religious aspects.
So, to see somebody talking about the Roman cult, what they mean is like religion in the Roman Empire.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Right.
Right, to distinguish that, or people who want to talk about the cult culture distinction
or relationship or that kind of thing.
They're using cult to refer to elements of a society or culture that are, quote, unquote,
religious, which, as we've pointed out, is a very modern thing to try to separate those out,
but people do it, and they use the word cult to refer to it.
Yeah, and all the money...
every furchic cultic practices, which again just means the stuff having to do with what we would call religion.
You know, or a cultic center that would be like a temple or a sacred grove, you know, again, all that sort of stuff.
This is all related to what mystery cult is, but it doesn't exhaust that.
So like what exactly does is a mystery cult when we're talking about the ancient world.
It's when you drive around with your dog and like four of your friends in a van solving this
And you didn't warm you that joke during our briefing earlier.
I save all my best material for live.
Those meddling kids.
No.
So, mystery called the purpose of having the phrase mystery called, right, is to the mystery
cults, for example, that we're going to talk about tonight, involve pagan gods, mostly,
right?
You
in gods that are also worshiped outside of the mystery cult. Right? So if you think about
one of them, one of the major ones is going to involve the Greek goddess Demeter.
Demeter goes way back in certain regions of basically, originally Asia Minor mostly.
but other parts of the Greek world as well.
as a harvest goddess, right, an earth goddess, this kind of thing, very sort of standard
goddess worship kind of tropes that you find way back.
Yeah, you got sacrifices.
The community coming together around a temple, like this is what the community
harvest festivals.
Yeah, normal things.
All the usual things.
And then in one particular place, it will be talking about this more in the second half
in detail, but in one particular play.
this particular type of ritual observance surrounding the worship of
Demeter springs up. And so that particular form of worship in that particular
place which goes on for centuries, right, but that particular worship of that
particular place is referred to as a mystery cult to distinguish it from that
That sort of broader standard.
pagan worship. And we'll see the same thing with gods like Dionysus and some other guy, right?
There's sort of the standard regular
pagan worship, but then in particular places
there come to be these particular types of
observance that are categorized together as mystery cults and then you will refer to
the mysteries of a particular god or a particular place to distinguish that from just the standard worship of that.
that God or goddess.
Yeah.
And so what are some factors that differentiate those two?
Well, the broad standard pagan worship of, say,
Demeter is going to involve like a big harvest festival
in a city that has a temple to the goddess Demeter.
And people from the surrounding villages,
people who live in the city,
people who have moved to the city,
people visiting the city at the time,
We'll all gather and offer sacrifice.
Propheises to Demeter and have a big feast and eat together and do your sort of standard pagan communal
Public worship and this is part of the life of the city
Yeah, and it's it's calendrical like it happens every year or you know over a few months or something like this
It's it's part of the normal rhythms of life and people all experience this together
Right, so it's public in the very original sense, right, it's of the people right like
whereas
the mystery
those observances are private in the sense that they are limited to certain people who meet certain requirements, certain prerequisites have gone through particular processes and things.
They're not open to the general public, they're subject of a few individuals.
Now sometimes they're sort of housed within.
So for example, again, we'll go into more detail in the second half.
The mystery is related.
a demeter, there was also at the same time that those private rights were being done.
In that area, there would be a big public feast that the general Hoy Palloy could all
pun intended.
Could we all go participate in, right?
But the mysteries were then this other aspect, this other private aspect.
And relatedly, of course, the sort of public worship of
the general cult, as opposed to the mystery cult, was collective. It was based around the
group doing it together, the city celebrating it together, the region celebrating it together,
communal meals at the Eidel's Temple, broad-based, and a big part of the purpose of it was
forming and strengthening community bonds, right, with each other and with the demon they were
we're worshiping.
Right.
So that was the goal, right?
Whereas the mystery cults are oriented toward the individual, right?
Because as you'd expect, related to them being private, there are select individuals
who have this personal experience.
The rituals are aimed at the person having that personal experience.
Yeah.
becoming an initiator is like a personal...
achievement. It's something you have accomplished, right? Something that you have achieved,
you've received that the vast majority of other people have not.
Yeah, and it's, and because it's not part of the sort of the cyclic public life,
it's also something that you just go through once, right? So I was trying to think about what the
kind of the, something that might be immediately analogous for some people would be, maybe,
If someone goes and is not perfectly analogous,
like they go on some kind of like a spiritual retreat,
like someone invites you to go to the desert
to go do a peyote thing with them.
Right?
That it's this private thing.
You want to go to the desert.
It's this private thing that people go to experience
this one time and it sort of changes you
and uh...
but no one there maintains,
it's not a community thing after that.
It's not like you might have your peyote buddy
as a whatever, but it's not really like that.
It's not a community living together
and doing these things and being bound together.
It's something that you went and did for you.
Yeah.
It's a white tourist, right?
Right?
Right.
Yeah.
I mean you can think that there are
We do have rights of initiation now in a civic life, right?
For example, going and getting your driver's license.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, sure, of course.
You know, driver's head, right?
Like, now that's, you know, my whole driver's head
thing was a wild experience because our driver's head
instructor was an elderly chain-smoking woman who let us
play the radio the car as long as she could roll the
window down its smoke.
I feel like this is the beginning of some kind of...
late 80s, you know, high school film or whatever.
Yeah, oh yeah, she'd like me cussing out
all the other drivers like what they cut us off.
It's so, it's kind of amazing.
But anyway, I won't go further down that rabbit trail.
Yeah.
But also, yeah, there are, I was just saying people
who, one time writes an initiation like that.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And the other thing is that people who go through
these mysteries do not in any way see themselves
now belonging to a different religion.
than the rest of their community.
Right.
You know, in as much as that is a thing,
it's either an element of or kind of related to
or just a thing that you did, you know,
it's not like, oh, I joined this.
You're not joining anything actually
by going through a mystery, a mystery cult, you know.
Right. Like the initiates didn't get together
and do a secret handshake to identify each other.
Yeah.
Yeah, you know.
talk about some secret knowledge they'd received because the knowledge as we go to detail you'll see this the knowledge they receive is like an experience.
Yeah, right. So you can call it knowledge, but it's like an experiential kind of knowledge. It's not like, oh, we revealed some secret truth to you, you know,
The Earth was colonized by aliens, you know, thousands of years ago and Adam and Eve escaped from an alien ship and brought with them.
this apple of Eden that you can use to take free will away from humanity or something.
Just a spin an example off the top of my head.
There was no like, oh, here's the secret history of the world that no one knows and only
the few of us initiated know it.
It's kind of a propositional truth kind of idea.
It was all shared and experienced, but not together.
Yeah.
It's not that you all went through this shared experience together and now that is bonded
you together.
It's quite the opposite of that.
Yeah.
You were isolated and had this experience by yourself, right?
But by how it works.
And so people in the mysteries who had been initiated could come back to like assist.
And I mean, assist in a very pragmatic way, right?
Like, the function is for the next initiate, right?
The next initiates.
they didn't under
go it again. Yeah because the idea is try to have the experience again. You already got it.
You have you know you have you have ascended on some level right you're exalted already. You
know you wouldn't do it again. And so this is in some ways and what we're going to talk about
now is review but it's review of something we haven't talked about on the show for a while.
But if you go a few years back of the show you'll find us talking about it and talking about it in
in more detail than we're going to talk about it.
Now, but in certain ways, what's going on because of these differences, what's going on in a mystery cult, is kind of an inversion of the way ritual normally works in human society.
So, we've talked about before that the way the way ritual primarily works is that through
ritual which is repeated ordered activity.
right? And we usually use it in some kind of religious sense, but it doesn't have to be, right?
There's a lot of other sub-rituals. Yeah, and it can run amok, right? So, sort of the principle
that causes the principle in human nature that causes ritual to work this way can run amok,
and then you end up with, for example, a lot of people who suffer from obsessive-compulsive disorder,
compose elaborate rituals, right, over small things like
and washing and locking doors and, right,
all kinds of things like that, right,
in order to maintain like their lives in their minds,
for example.
So they could write a mock,
but the basic principle in human nature
is that this kind of repeated order activity
shapes the way we see the world.
And what we mean by that,
shapes the way you see the world is
Every experience we have.
have is filtered through a grid. We do not have any bare objective experiences. As
we said before, there's no view from nowhere. Yeah. Right. Everything you see, you see from
some particular perspective. Right. Things don't look at the very basic level. Things don't
look the same from above and from below.
They looked different.
right? And so everything was see everything we read. Definitely not going to go
down this rabbit trail for a while, but this is this is the fatal flaw of the
whole idea of solar scriptura. The idea that you could come to the Bible and
just read what's objectively in the Bible without it being colored by your past
experience by your life so far by the things you've learned by the way you've
learned to define words that you read.
Right? Like, obviously all of that. So, we're, you know, we can argue about when you're
born, but from not long after you're born, you are not a blank slate anymore. You're
going to be wanting to say you're born that way, John Locke. By the time you remember anything,
you're not that way anymore. Right? That's, you have a set of experiences and you have
a language that your
learning to think in and you have a right and all of those are going to shape this, right?
And so we've talked before like the main categories of things that help shape that grid are language,
right? The way you name things and the way names of things are related to each other
conceptually, right? That covers how you perceive those things.
and music and art, which both shape the way you see and interpret things.
And by C I mean sense.
So I mean C here, taste, touch, right.
You associate, you start to associate particular smells and taste and sounds with certain things,
right.
And then finally the fourth one is ritual.
And ritual is an overarching one because ritual...
can include language, music, and art.
So just to use one example of a ritual, the Orthodox divine
liturgy, it takes place in a setting where there
is iconography and certain types of architecture.
And there is obviously music of a certain type.
And there is particular liturgical language,
not meaning what language liturgy is done in,
but there are a-
words that mean something within that context. Right, there are technical terms to find
liturgy words. Right. Sometimes there are words that are not commonly used outside of
that setting by many people. I don't hear people use the word remission very often if they're
not talking about sins at a liturgical service. Yeah. Or sometimes there are just words
that have a different meaning in that context.
Right, where there's some subtle shift in meaning where, okay, yeah, the way you normally use that word it's x but here we're using it to refer to
This other thing, right
That might be like spirit which means something very different in a peperally or the divine liturgy, right?
Right
That's way
But the other thing about ritual the other thing about ritual is that
that.
ritual can be used deliberately
to
reshape
perceptions.
Yeah, yeah, right
and this is part of how the how for example cults in the contemporary sense of the word work
Right the cult leader could struck some kind of communal life for the people
that is aimed at whatever his goals are, which as we said inevitably become
sex. But that's everything is structured. He structures the communal life of the people
and isolates them from outside influences. That's almost always a he so that they can
control their very perception of reality. Now music and art and language by themselves do this,
But it's often less deliberate in the sense that...
ostensibly at least, right, unless you're trapped in an elevator.
We choose what music we're going to listen to, right?
We may not be aware of the effects that music is having on us.
We choose what kind of images to look at.
We may not be aware of how that's affecting us, but it is.
But that's still a consequence of our choice, right?
But ritual can very...
deliberately reframe the very way we experience things. And that's frankly the goal of, for example,
Orthodox services, right? Orthodox services are aimed at changing the way we perceive and interact
with the world. This is going to be a come-important later. And so part of one of the most important parts
of joining the Orthodox Church is submitting yourself.
to Christ's church, to be reformed.
Yeah, to be reshaped.
Which is, which is, which is the way,
when we say things like,
you can't just read it all in books,
this is part of what we mean by that.
Unless you go through the rituals
and experience the ritual life of the church,
your point of view, at the very least,
Your point of view is not the
point of view of the church.
Right. The way I read things, the way I see things,
the way I hear things, the way I interpret things,
the way I assess the meaning of things is wrong.
Yeah.
And I have to therefore submit to that being corrected.
And that's not just a question of logical propositions.
Right.
Of, I think A is true, but actually B is true.
So someone needs to correct me.
I need to believe that B is true.
No.
I believe that A is true, right?
But the way I understand A or B or anything else, right?
My way of understanding it is wrong.
Yeah, it's not just the data.
So even if B is absolutely true, if you just tell me B, I won't understand B correctly.
Right?
I have to you ultimately have to enter in.
a community. It's within the ritual life of a community that all these things make sense.
Right? And they can't totally be underserved from outside. But we may have noticed
I've just said community a whole bunch of times. Yeah. Yeah. Right. And collective and group
and shared life. And that's the way pagan religion works too. It's just conforming you to something
other than Christ.
right? It's conforming you to the spirits that those religions are
worshiping, right? But as we said, mystery, a mystery called by definition is not
doing that collective thing. Yeah, it's for you. Right, it's you being set apart as
an individual in part by having this experience that others have not had.
Right, that's part of the whole idea.
Right, is that this is going to make...
you different than other people. Not this is going to bond you together with other people.
Right? And shape how all of you live together and think together and see things together.
Right? And so it is about, as we said, inducing a particular experience.
And then rather than participating in a way of life that re-offrames how you experience the world,
You have
an experience that is supposed to reframe the way you think about your life.
So, it's almost a direct inversion. And to get to the heart of the matter, pretty much
all of the mystery cults are Catholic.
Yeah, meaning there's some underground element, so to speak, because an underworld element.
right, that this is stuff involving death.
Not a near death experience the way we talk about it now, but not totally dissimilar to that.
Right?
Well, when we talk about near death experiences, currently we talk about, oh, somebody was,
you know, medically dead for two minutes and they come out of it.
And during that time when, you know, they flatlined and things said they were technically
Dad.
come back reporting having had some experience. And often that's an experience of a spiritual
nature, right? That's not what we're talking about. Although it's not like I said, not
totally dissimilar from that. This was more, this is more about inducing a dear death experience
in the sense of someone's in a horrible car wreck and emerges alive, right? Someone in
war or in some other contexts is getting shot at.
and almost dies but doesn't. Someone survives a plane crash that most of the other people don't.
That kind of near dead experience. And so you can understand how, if you think about people who
have had those experiences I just listed, that kind of reframes how they think about their life.
right? I mean, they say you almost die. Your life flashes before your eyes. I mean, I've, I've, I've, I've
I've talked to multiple people.
I mean, one gets this in pastoral ministry
where if they almost die, you know,
maybe they have a disease, maybe they have, you know,
whatever, I almost died on the operating table,
or this kind of thing, they often rethink
how the way that they live and they live in a different way.
They see life differently after that.
Right.
And so the mystery cults fundamentally are about
inducing that kind of experience in a person.
Yeah.
giving a person.
than that kind of experience.
And so the experience itself is the thing,
is what they're after and what they're about.
So it's not about just objectively
having participated in the ritual.
Right, this is definitely a,
I'm doing something for me, kind of thing.
Right, right.
Like you think about pledging a fr-
You go through some series of ordeals, right?
And now you're a member, right?
But the experience of the ordeals is not really
ultimately what it's about.
Yeah.
It's about you becoming a member.
Right.
And you go through those ordeals with a group of people, right?
And it bonds you together with those people.
Yeah, I mean, I think in some ways a certain parallel would be, for instance,
instance people who
people who do hallucinogenic drugs to achieve a higher state of consciousness
or something like that. That's not a parallel. It's kind of on the nose. Yes,
that's true as we'll discover. Most people these days are not doing that.
There's no conception of a mystery call. Yeah, but I mean, I you know, it's
come back now it's it's a I don't quite say it's
respectable, but there's some people that are presenting themselves as respectable, who
will say things like, like for instance, Alex O'Connor, the guy, what is he called
himself, Cosmic Skeptic.
I think he did mushrooms or something like that and said that he understood things better.
He understood something.
He achieved something in doing that.
You know?
Yeah.
Yeah, I don't know, I took with him I interpret that a little bit.
differently, but really, I don't know, I don't know his work well, but I, I was, well,
yeah, interviewers. So there are some, there are some folks out there, especially now, right?
I'm talking about younger people now, right? Cause it had been a while before, well, it
had been a while. It had been ever since anybody was really raised without religion. Yeah.
Yeah, you know what I mean like yeah, this is a new that's a rare occur that's better rare
and human history, right?
People like rebel against the religion they were raised in,
right?
So you think about something like Voltaire who hated Christianity
who still raised Roman Catholic, right?
Like he just hated it, rejected it, right?
Or Thomas Jefferson with, you know,
Protestantism or whatever, right?
They were raised with some religious didn't like it.
I'm not talking about that.
I'm talking about someone who was raised
without any religion, right?
Which we now have increasingly.
in the world, especially in the United States and Europe, right?
And those folks mostly have no religious sensibility.
And what I mean by that is they don't think in those categories at all.
Yeah, I think they might think about consciousness and the mind and this kind of thing.
And I think for those people, if they decided to do some kind of drugs as part of that, they think of it as tinkering with that.
Yeah.
Yeah, so they just, they don't have a religious sensibility.
Like they don't, if you see them trying to talk about
religion in the world, they always turn it into politics
or they turn it into something that they do have
more of a sense of, right?
And it's not that they're like horrible people
with no soul unless they're gingers.
It's that they just don't have that sensibility,
right?
doesn't. So.
think about something that just doesn't appeal to you, right? Like ballet just does not appeal
to me. I have no sense of ballet. Despite me, if you made me go to a ballet and I sat there,
I would not be able to tell you whether it was a good one or a bad one. Despite being
a word-winning ballroom dancer, Father Stephen, I can't believe it. Yes. A strictly ballroom.
No, no, no, no, man. Right? That's just me. It's like a wrong ballet. I think it just means
I have no sense of it, right?
Like, I could watch it up...
Unless somebody just, you know, trips and falls, right?
Like I'm not gonna be able to know like,
oh, that was an exquisite whatever maneuver, right?
Or figure skating.
My sister's watch figure skating.
I don't know what a quadruple
lots looks like even, right?
Like, no clue, right?
So I just, I have no sensibility for it, right?
So like me watching it is a waste of my time
because I don't, I have no sense of it, right?
These folks are that way with relief.
And I think some of those folks, when they do psychedelics, that's the first time they've
had anything even approximating in any even rough way a religious experience.
And so it sort of opens up this category, right?
if somehow I did get roped into going to a ballet.
And for some reason,
that particular night, something I saw
and it was just the most beautiful thing I had ever seen, right?
Like maybe I'm developing a sense for ballet, right?
But in this case, the inklings of developing
some kind of religious sensibility
to someone who previously didn't have one, right?
That's part of what I think is going on there.
So all that is to say, I think that's a little different
what's going on here because
Maybe in most cases I think these people had since they were in the broad run of paganisms
They paganism they had some kind of religious. Yeah, yeah, that's something. I mean some analog. It's not a yeah
But but
Again, this isn't about being able to just point at objectively right objectively I took drivers at I took the written tests
Now I have my driver's license
right
Objectively, I went through the process. I joined this fraternity. I'm a frat brother for a sorority sister
Right
Where there's this objective thing I did these steps now. This is the thing right
It's and there was an experience involved there and that experience did certain things like bond me together with my frat brothers
or sorority scissors, we got to be even handed here.
Right, diversity, equity, inclusion.
Or now I am one of the people who has a driver's license
so I can get on a plane.
That's what they're for as you know.
Yes.
Start racking up those frequent flyer miles.
Right, but the experience, right,
me going through drivers head with my friend Dave,
Right, they have helped strengthen.
within the friendship between me and Dave.
That's a teenager, right?
But that was not the purpose.
The purpose of me going through driver's head
was to get a driver's license,
not to hang out with Dave.
Yeah, right?
Dave's not here, man.
But the purpose of entering the Fraterior sorority,
and the initiation is not just to have an experience.
It's to bond.
together with your crap brothers and sisters, right? That's the goal is to make you part of this group.
So with the mystery called the purpose of being initiated in the mysteries is just to have the
experience of being initiated in the in the mysteries. Yeah. Right. It's the difference between having
a few drinks at a party to lubricate your socializing versus having a few drinks at home by yourself
Hmm, just to get BOMF.
Yeah. Right. So what are the great family oriented analogies can I draw? But we give
parental advisory. So your kids should be listening to this anyway. Especially when
we get in the next half. This half hasn't been hasn't been bad at all in comparison.
Yeah, no, you're being loaded into a false sense of security.
That's right.
What we...
start the second half you better not bring your kids. That's I'm just hide your wife.
But so this and the way this experience, this sort of as we said near death experience of
almost dying of coming to the cusp of death and then pulling away, right, was not just a spiritual
counter in the sense that in broader paganism.
Right, the ritual life of broader paganism. You're having an encounter with
The spirit in the woods or in the spring or in the fountain or you're having
You know any counter with the the God or the goddess, right of some sort but not just the spirits themselves but
You're having a counter with the whole spiritual world particularly the underworld
So it's not just oh I almost died like in a biological sense, right?
my life has a terminus I need to rethink.
things, but also you're sort of coming right up to the gate of the underworld and then
turning back and you get sort of a glimpse of it is the idea.
And so it's, I have seen now, right, the fate that awaits me in all flesh, right?
Beyond just our sort of modern biological sense of that.
Yeah, and you have to imagine that there's probably a certain level of thrill seeking.
that kind of goes into some of this, you know?
Oh yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
I've never seen flatliners, but that's what I imagine
the movie is about.
Is that what it's about?
Have you seen it?
I assume you've seen it.
It's kind of, well okay, so there's the original,
there's a remake, the remake is terrible.
Okay, I've never seen either.
But the original is kind of a classic, yes, except,
yeah, the original actually would kind of pair
a little well with this,
that they're kind of
real seeking and they end up encountering things in the spiritual world.
Yeah.
Maybe that they didn't want to.
Little did they know.
But there is the whole Julia Roberts issue.
Well, I don't like looking.
I don't like looking at Julia Roberts.
I was going to say, I was going to leave that as a cliffhanger.
Oh, no.
Yeah.
I mean, our mutual friend, DeConser from Roland, the
believes that Julia Roberts can unhinge your jaw and swallow
humans like an anaconda.
See, now this is what the only thing we've ever had in common
because I used to say that Julia Roberts looks like she
could eat a whole apple.
Well, there you are.
So see, apparently we share one insight.
There is something.
Yes, you can come together on this.
It's all the cunt of the Roberts.
That's right.
So yeah.
Well, and you know what about breakfast at Tiffany's?
Hmm.
Is that...
recall I think we both kind of like that that that song has a very specific
reference in my head because of I was going through some stuff man when I came out
that horrible summer when that was played continually everywhere everywhere
everywhere everywhere all right well on that cliffhanger then we're not gonna
reveal any details about that from my life we're gonna take our first break and
And we'll be right back on this.
It's getting
Weirder episode of The Lord of Spirit's podcast.
Hi, this is Genevieve, the director of development at Ancient Faith Ministries.
I want to wish you all a warm and spiritually nourishing Christmas season.
As we journey through the sacred nativity fast towards the birth of Christ, I pray you are filled
with hope awaiting the light of the world.
Throughout history, Christians have understood that the light we received is meant to be shared
with others as a gift.
St. Nicholas secretly brought hope to families in need and St. Lucia demonstrated how we can
be light bears.
world of darkness. Here at Ancient Faith we are honored to edify,
evangelize, educate and engage countless seekers, believers in those
hungry, prespecial nourishment. Every donation no matter how modest
becomes a light that we pass forward to our listeners. As you prepare for
the need to be, would you consider giving the gift of light to Ancient Faith?
Your gift, whether 25, 50, or 100, joins with the offerings of countless
others to ensure that Christ's light continues to be lit and shared.
please visit ancientfade.com and click support on the
hot menu. Together we are Light Bears. Together we prepare the way of the Lord.
Blessed Nativity to you and yours and thank you so much for your generosity.
Hey welcome back. It's the second half of this pre-recorded episode of the Lord
Spirit's podcast we're talking about. Mystery cults in the ancient world and
this is the half where the parental advisory we delivered in the first half is
really gonna kick in.
So full effect yeah, yeah, so again, please
Be this tall to ride this ride. Yeah parents. Please review this before you listen to it with your kids
Because what we're spring it on your things give it guests. Yeah, yeah, exactly
We're not gonna be explicit, but we are gonna be straightforward
so because here's the thing you're sitting there right now, especially if you're out the West Coast
right as you're hearing this premiere and
and you're thinking to yourself
We're gonna sit down for dinner. Crazy uncles gonna bring up politics. This is all gonna go south
Listen play this in the background stunned silence
Much better things giving us exactly
Wait, what wait what what yes? Yes, just people
Awkwardly looking at one another I do kind of love it when that happens not because again
not because it's lured but because
I think what it does is it makes people realize that a lot of our assumptions about the
ancient world are all wrong or significantly wrong.
Yes.
Or at least significantly bowedlarized.
Yeah.
We have this idea of these beautiful white columns and all this kind of stuff which weren't
white.
They were painted garish colors.
But it turns out that it was right.
Right.
I mean it turns out that it was a pretty night.
marriage world in fact for most people. For most people.
So this doesn't play into your nice rhetoric about the world was
this this beautiful paradise of of pagan nature lovers. And then
these horrible Christians came in and started oppressing all
the women's. Yeah, no, I mean, I mean, yeah, getting rid of
slavery. Oh, no, wait, that doesn't work either. Right. Yeah, I
I guess we should just make ours.
Samuel Amul-Nod towards Dominion by Tom Holland if you want to get the overarching sweep about what the ancient world was actually like and how Christianity completely changed the whole world.
Yeah, whether you're Christian or not.
So, alright, well, let's get into some details about mystery culture.
So, I mean, they're so mysterious, they're so secret and stuff.
How do we know anything about them other than what people say?
They're terribly mysterious.
Look.
the sphinx. Yeah, so while we mentioned last time when we were talking about
Mithrais, that part of the reason, right, we don't have any texts for
Mithraism because they were either passively not copied and maintained or
more antagonistically destroyed, probably a mixture of both, right. I'm not
saying one or those two is what happened. I'm saying both probably happened in
different places over time.
And we didn't have anybody really rat out what was going on, right?
There was no rat, no stooly, no narc, no tattletail, right, who, uh, no snitch, right, who came and told everybody what was going on.
Not so with some of the other mystery cults.
And so the biggest rat of the ancient world was a fellow named...
Appalais. Yes, who wrote a book with, and we're not kidding about this, a title, The Golden
Ass. Yes, The Golden Ass. I have so many jokes that I can't tell live on the air because
I know it's pre-recorded. They'll get edited out. So I'm not even going to bother. But I
think it should be mentioned though that actually Appalais's name for his book is the Metamorphoses.
of it. Yeah, right.
I don't know. Right, right? But I guess, I guess the golden ass title we get from St. Augustine.
He's the one who refers to it as the golden ass. And it's kind of a novel.
Well, yeah, it does, it is the story of a guy who gets turned into a donkey.
Yes. Right.
Magically. Right.
So I mean, that's, that's the use, it's the biblical use of the word ass.
Correct.
Exactly.
that were which still may be snicker.
Yes.
Well, it every
the 10 commandments were read. But yeah, I mean, it's funny. I mean, almost every culture has this
sense that donkeys are, you know, kind of goofy and low and ridiculous and stupid and stubborn.
Call someone that it's an insult, you know, it seems to be almost universal throughout time and
space, which of course are both illusions of it as we've covered been passed. But yes, by Appalais,
Transistor-
The historical reality of donkeys.
Yes.
Um, the, you have a platonic form,
eternal platonic form of the donkey.
Um, so yeah, so, uh, this work, uh,
is based for a couple of things.
Uh, for those of you who are CS Lewis fans,
which, I don't know, statistically is at least the majority,
if not the super majority of you.
Yeah, a certain Venn diagram.
Yes, like I am not counted among you unfortunately, but you're I know you're there
The reason you love this is because this is where the story of Cupid and psyche is right
Which CS Lewis wouldn't have had access to otherwise and so you wouldn't have your favorite book
It is his best book
Till we have faces is his best book
The only books of his I really love are the
the space trilogy, which are the ones that no one else likes.
I don't know.
People like him, although I like the first two better than the third.
The third, I mean, the third, there was a lot about it that I appreciated.
You know, like I'm like, okay, I see what you're doing here.
But I just, I don't know, I didn't like it.
What can I say?
Well, the third one, he gets political and then I feel betrayed.
That's ironic coming from you.
Yes.
I already used so I
Aaronic sometimes.
It really is.
Okay.
But yes, why are we looking at this book?
Like what does it have to do with the story?
Anyway, the story of Cupid is psyche is in there as a story within the story.
Yeah.
Right.
The broader story being this guy who is becoming a donkey and then gets changed back.
But he over the course of the story is initiated first into the mysteries of ISIS and then
when he goes to Rome and is initiated into the mystery.
of Osiris and become sort of a priest, right, within the mystery cult. And in the context of
narrating that, Appalais goes into full detail about all the things that happened in these
initiation rights. Right. So he doesn't just say it happens like he describes the whole thing in detail.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. And thereby is a stool pigeon. Sort of leaks everything.
Now, how do we know how would he know he's not making it up?
How do we know that well part of how we know is how to make it so this is the only description this detail that we have
Okay, right for any mystery cult so we don't have anything but compare it completely against
Right, but there are bits and pieces of information and details that we have about various mystery cults
right little bits and pieces of different sources here and there and
and all of those little bit
and pieces from all over the place, I'll check out with this detailed description.
Okay, so they're basically mutually compatible. This is the data we have.
If there's anything that we know. So broadly accepted. Yeah, if there's anything we know about
mystery cults, this is where we know it from. Right, it's broadly accepted that at least in the broad
strokes, this is what's going on versions of this variations on these themes are what is going on
in mystery cults.
Okay.
Right.
And so.
So the rest of this half, we're going to be talking about some of those variations in different
mystery cults.
Right.
But the broad strokes, right?
And so a lot of the broad strokes we were talking about in the first half, right, like
about the near death experience part and that kind of thing, we're getting from primarily
the golden ass as reinforced by other sources.
Okay.
Right.
All right.
Now, and another part of this is of course that, you know, these are the
the mysteries of ISIS and the mysteries of Osiris,
these are not native Egyptian religious forms.
Yeah, I mean, it's almost like in religious terms,
it's almost like a Greek fan fiction
of Egyptian religion sort of, right?
It would that sort of yeah, like like sort of Greeks
who find Egyptian religions super cool
and so they kind of come up with this stuff
to participate in it.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Richard Geer and Buddhism.
Wow. That's continuing where we just ended the first half, right?
Or like when Madonna got into Kabbalah.
Oh, yeah, that was hilarious.
Yes, right. Like that kind of thing.
Yeah. But then it becomes established.
Yeah.
Or who did the Beatles meet with?
But they beat with the yogi at one point.
Anyway, that kind of there's got to be a Scientology joke in here somewhere, but I'm just not coming to be but I
Feel like that's parallel. I think I think we already covered Scientology with the whole all cults become sex cults
That is yes, but moving I'm gonna get sued now. That's awesome by the
Scientologists. I mean yes, that's that's what we do on the internet since the 90s
Then I'll know I have finally arrived all hail operation clam bake
That's what I have to say about all of that.
So.
But yeah, so this isn't a native Egyptian thing. This is a product of under the Talamis, right?
Holognic culture sort of interfacing with and
Having some fun with native Egyptian religious tradition and a reminder everybody
The Talamis are a Greek dynasty ruling Egypt like Cleopatra. William Patro was Greek one of those. Yes, she was a Greek
And if you've seen her silhouette on coins, which you can see we have the coins
She was definitely Greek.
Oh yes.
She had a Greek profile.
Yes, right.
Which one of my favorite issues of the Astrix and Oblix comics makes much of the shape of
the nose of Cleopatra.
Yes.
It's, yeah, yeah, yeah.
It's time to memorize.
So yes, not that anyone who works for the BBC listens to this.
but stop it with a stunt casting.
Um,
so, uh, the other, the other interesting source,
interesting to listeners of this podcast regarding the mysteries of Isis O'Syres.
And this was a huge, wonderful surprise to me.
Yes, I couldn't believe it.
I couldn't believe it.
A little story told by Josephus in antiquities.
I know, which is, like, like my grandmother had Josephus on her bookshelf.
Yes, my late grandmother.
She never told me about it.
So, and in terms of the parental advisory, this is going to be a good test case because
if this one causes you an issue, it's all downhill from here people for the rest of this
house.
Okay.
Just telling you now.
So what is Josephus about?
Josephus tells a story about this certain fellow, this certain Roman who, meaning living
in Rome itself named Mundus.
It's relatable as Mr.
world. Yes. And so he is infatuated with a young lady in Rome and said object of his
affections had no interest in him. Right. Not unrequited love as it was. Yes. And so he
He can cock to the scheme for himself.
And got her to decide to participate in the mysteries of Osiris.
I mean, most guys would just go down and buy a love potion from the local Aphrodite.
Yes.
Yes, but not not Mundus.
Not our boy Mundus.
He gets her, oh you need to go and do, be initiated into the mysteries of Osiris at this
the temple for the mysteries of Osiris and Rome.
So she decides to do this.
And in the context of this mystery initiation,
Mundus has a sexual intercourse with her
under the guise of she believes she is having sexual relations
with the God of Nupis.
See, this is a good tie-in with our giants episode
from five years ago.
Yes, so
She thinks she's just making Nephilim, right?
Whereas he is using subterfuge,
as a nerd to get with his crush.
So that happened, then apparently the Emperor Tiberius found out about it.
Yes, the morals of Rome have been affronted by this terrible act.
Yes, yes. And Tiberius.
Decides that this is terrible. We could not have such things going on
The Roman people must show more stoic self-restraight than this
On both sides and so had the temple
Destroyed had the temple leveled where it happened and all of the people involved
Mundus the woman
The the priests and priestesses of the temple who were involved had all of them crucified
That'll show them
Yes. And this is kind of you know you may be wondering why would Josephus our friend the
Pharisee? Right. Right. Who are Protestant friends treat as infallible on the biblical
can? I know. More important. My father's. I mean it why would he relate such a tale?
Yeah. I mean it's because it makes the emperor look great. And that's what this guy is
Right, well it makes...
Pagan's look bad as compared to Jews,
but without blaming the pagan emperor.
Yeah.
Right?
So he can say as Jewishers, look, we Jews,
we don't do stuff like that.
Yeah.
And, you know, the emperor doesn't do anything.
And you owe great wise emperor.
You know, you know this.
That's why I see that's how this is gets,
this kind of thing gets punished.
But the Pagan's get up to that kind of stuff.
So he continues his Roman bootlicking
or sandalicking, in this case.
Right.
This is not a passage from Josephus that your Baptist preacher is probably going to mention
on Sunday morning when he's...
No. In fact, probably no passage from Josephus other than his canon list.
Yeah. Right.
And his claim that every Jew knows that that is the canon of Scripture from their birth.
That's Platonic knowledge right there.
Yes. Other than that.
Right.
you never get quoted by both Producing.
Yeah, because there's a...
And so by the way everybody no there's all got yeah as we just saw there's all kinds of thing
He writes a lot about the history of the Herodian dynasty so there's plenty of there's stuff. Yeah
All right, so so what what else we got what are the kinds of
Shmanigans are they up to there?
What else you can oh but we need to get it's worse right?
So the mysteries of Isis and Osiris although we have this from Apaleus
Yes, that's not...
the sort of biggest and most famous.
Mystery called the biggest and most famous mystery
called the Goes on for the longest period of time
are the Ellucinian mysteries.
Yeah, this is the big one.
Yes.
And the Ellucinian mysteries are this is what we were referring
to at the beginning of the show in terms of Demeter.
So this is the Ellucinian mysteries revolve around the story
in particular of demeter and
Persephone. Yeah, and just for those of you who haven't read that stuff recently the basic outline of the story. How dare you?
I know I know I know what's wrong with you guys need to be correct with all these things. I
Mean you've had thousands of years to read these texts. So yes, yes, these are the classic. That's right
So so the the basic story of Demeter and Persephone is that Persephone is her daughter
So Demeter is the this fertility in harvest goddess right and her daughter is Persephone and Persephone is abducted by Hades
the God of the underworld who thinks that Persephone is all that. And while
Persephone is in the underworld.
Hades gets her to eat some, man, I can see it in my head,
but now it's...
Pomergranate is needed.
Yes, Pomergranate seeds and six of them, it's six, right?
I think, and so as a result of her eating stuff
in the underworld, which, I mean,
you wanna read this in ritual terms, right?
She's in communion with the God, okay.
As a result of her eating stuff in the-
underworld, then she's bound to him and she is his wife. But then, you know,
Demeter basically threatens to kind of destroy the world with endless winter.
As a result of this, and the gods kind of say, look, Demeter, you can't do
that. This is bad. And so deal has worked out sort of a time share.
Custody deal. Yes. Yes. A custody deal over Persephone, where Persephone will
live in the underworld for a number of months with Hades, and then, you know,
with her mom, Demeter, and the other months. And this kind of, you know, the way
that often people talk about.
This explains the seasons.
So that's an element of the story.
But the part of this that's really interesting
in terms of mystery cult stuff
is that Persephone takes this journey into the underworld
and has experiences there.
And that's the thing that they're really kind of interested in
for this.
And then emerges in the spring.
Yeah.
And so, yeah, we have to remember,
People read this story now mythologically.
Yeah. So they do the largely dumb dumb. Well, they know have signs. So they think fall and winter are
goddess crying, right? Yeah. Um, and like, okay. But that's the dumb dumb version. Yeah. No, this is what it's about.
The reason why the story has power for people is because they participate in it richly. And of course,
you know, on some level, everyone's participating in this with, you know, the cycle of regular
our feet and stuff.
But you're all the harvest festivals for them.
This particular participation is about this element of it,
this underworld-dirty element.
It's about sharing the experience of Persephone,
journeying into the underworld,
not just celebrating the harvest with
Demeter and giving her credit for it,
which is the more broad concept.
Yeah. And so this is much deeper than just,
other they don't have science.
This is linking together the cycles of human life,
birth and death with the cycles of nature, right?
There's a lot more going on here, right?
And again, yeah, we're talking about a mystery
called the participates in that,
particularly through the vehicle of the person of Persephone
and being sort of united or having that experience.
Now
The Greeks themselves and still some historians think this goes all the way back to like Bronze
Age Minoan civilization.
Yes, that would be super duper early.
Yes.
That's not most people though.
Right.
And you can understand why the Greeks would think everything is older than it is.
Right?
Sure.
You don't understand that, that you haven't spent a lot of time.
in an Orthodox church.
Because in an Orthodox church,
if you do something three times in a row,
your church now has a hundred year tradition
of doing that thing.
Right.
Like that's how it works.
That's how it was always been.
Like, it's the founding of the church
and it's always been that way.
In meeklenose.
Yeah.
It's sometimes that's true and often it's not, right?
sir.
So the Greeks thought everything stretched, but we've always done this, right?
And sometimes they went way back and sometimes not so far back.
Most people think now it started somewhere in the Mycenaean period.
Some version of this, right?
Not the full orbed thing, but some version of it.
And something that might actually be evidence of that.
Yeah, this is wild too.
is in the Book of Judges.
certain fellow named Jeff though.
So not a saint.
Not a saint.
Not even a little bit.
Although I say every time I say this about Jeff that at Samson,
people go crazy about Samson.
This is part of my proof that this is just me ruining their Sunday school.
That's all they're mad about.
I never hear anything back about Jeff though.
Yeah, it was literally in the same list and used in the same way.
Like they can make all those
all the same arguments. Yeah. For Jeff, they think they could make a better case because
there are fewer church fathers who just directly say that Jeff that isn't a saint. Yeah.
Then there are who say directly that Samson is not. Yeah. Yeah. But at any rate, now we've
just ginned that up again because any time I save the name Samson, like there's another
round of it online. Like man, I'm living rent free in so many places. I've got more houses
Donald Trump. Yes.
Um, that, uh, so, uh, the story of Jeff that judges, first of all, people only are familiar,
even with half of it. Yes. There's a whole story about war with Moab that nobody remembers.
Yeah. The part that people remember is, of course, that Jeff that makes this oath that the first,
the first person that comes to him when he gets back from winning the battle. He didn't take a
How her a sheep was
going to come prodig out to be the kid.
Sacrifice to God.
And it turns out it's his daughter.
And so she says, let me take some time
to lament my virginity.
Basically, I'm not going to have gotten
to live a normal married life like everybody else.
So he gives her some time.
And then it doesn't.
It's not explicit in the text.
But it's heavily implied that he sacrifices her.
but then it also says that there is a
But feast day that's appointed, that's connected with this.
There's this commemoration that occurs.
There at the end, this is the other part that gets left off, right?
So just to do a couple of quick troubleshooting things, don't come at me with that.
He didn't sacrifice her.
She became a virgin at the temple.
There was no temple.
Yeah.
Are you telling me she became a pagan shrine prostitute?
That's better.
Anyway.
Yeah.
That's it.
Like what?
Um.
So, right.
And what you find actually,
if you read both the church fathers
and rabbinic interpretations of Jeff Tha,
is they all talk about the virtue of his daughter.
They don't talk about him.
Yeah, she's the hero in this story.
Right, she is presented as sort of parallel to Isaac
in the story of Abraham sacrificing his son
where she is sort of quiet and obedient
even to the point of death.
That's who they talk about.
Jeff the daughter as being a type of Christ, not Jeff the killing his daughter as being a type of Christ somehow
Weirdo. That may be why I don't get as much pushback
But anyway
But yeah, that it says at the end that there is this feast in the northern kingdom of Israel
That comes from this that they say comes from
Jeff the having done a human sacrifice with his daughter, this horrible
will act, right? Which, and yes, read the Torah, if you made a hasty or rash oath, you could
repent of it and offer animal sacrifices instead. But he didn't know that because Jeff was basically
an unreconstructed pagan if you read judges. So he commits this horrible act and there's this festival
where people go out looking for his daughter, looking for the missing, made in the missing daughter.
Okay, and they go out with torches doing this.
And this is exactly the thing you find at our reports
of the earliest stages of the Ellucinian mysteries.
The torchbearers are sort of an office
within the enactment of the mysteries throughout its history
and they go out looking for, in that case, Persephone.
Okay.
Uh, so...
Now, controversial part, in the same way, and this is especially obvious if you read it in Hebrew,
in the same way that the story of Samson, I'm not saying it's not a true story.
Story of Samson is a true story, okay?
But the way it's presented,
right, the way the story is told is as a parody of early stories of Heracles or Hercules.
Yeah.
in the same way.
in the same book, Judges, right?
The story of Jeff Tha is presented as an alternate origin,
an alternate horrible origin for this Hellenic pagan festival.
That eventually becomes the Ellucinian mysteries.
Why would anybody in Israel,
especially the Northern Kingdom,
be concerned with either of those things?
Remember Samson's...
the tribe of Dan. Yeah, which is the, you know, the basically pagan tribe. Yeah, the origin of
the anti-Christ, I mean, really a book of Revelation. It's the tribe that doesn't get to go into the
kingdom. But it's also the farthest north. Yeah, that's that's right. The northernmost of the
northern tribes. Right. Right. So why? Well, because the Danites, the Philistines are descended from
from the sea peoples, they're my synans.
So the pagan religion being practiced by the Philistines and the Danites and judges is
very clear that the Danites are practicing pagan religion.
It is abundantly clear.
It talks about them getting the ephod and hiring the priest to come and sacrifice to it,
hiring a Levite and all that.
That's all on the page in judges.
form of paganism is the
this early form of Hellenic paganism.
Early Hellenic paganism derived from what?
From Syrian paganism.
So there are cross-currants and assimilation
in Phoenicia, right, as you get up into the Syrian
and Hittite regions, right, where this stuff is all mixed.
The reason I say Samson being a parody,
by the way, is obviously, especially original Hebrew,
is that...
The original Hebrew is full of puns
Like deliberate puns and jokes
In the Samson story
Right that if you know Hebrew are that's telegraphing to you what this story is doing right
But yeah, if you're mad about that
Probably saying that
Send your angry
E-mails to Father Andrew.
And excerpt that.
Not so back to the L.U. City and Mystery's proper.
Yeah.
They're called the L.U. City and Mystery's not because if you may have noticed neither
Demeter nor Persephone are named L.U.S.
Yeah.
It's the name of a place.
Yes.
L.U.S. is the city.
Where are these mysteries to place?
And there were sort of two steps.
Right so if we continue by
not great driver's license analogy. You get your lurchers permit in midwinter. The end of January
beginning of February, you would go there if you wanted to be among the initiates that year.
Right at the festival proper. You'd go there at the end of January beginning of February
in midwinter. It's and offer pig sacrifices. They're actually piglet sacrifices. They're baby pigs.
you offer baby pigs to
demeter.
And this is, by the way, in case anyone is wondering where this is, this is in
this isn't the Athens area.
It's actually a suburb now of Athens.
So yeah, probably, you know,
Athens was smaller than so it was a city outside of Athens.
Yeah.
Athenian urban sprawl.
Is it?
So you go there you make
these mid-winter baby pigs sacrifices to demeter, right?
You're making these offerings to her
during her period of mourning, right?
Cause that's what the winner is supposed to be.
And then you come back at harvest time,
the next autumn.
And that's when the mysteries proper,
the initiations proper were held.
And so as we mentioned the end of the first half, this is about producing this ritual experience of death and rebirth.
So one of the reasons why most of these were performed underground and caverns and tunnels and things is not just the connection with Hades in the underworld, that's part of it.
part of it, but also because that was the place where you could get
absolute darkness. So I don't know if you've ever go and take any of these cave
tours and any of these famous cave systems in like Kentucky or I'd
girls back caverns. I did one on Guam. Okay normally you know you get down into
the cave system and there'll be about where they they warn you and then for
like a few seconds they turn the lights off. Yes and when I took and I'm not
kidding about this. When I took this tour on Guam and
they turn everything off, someone said, and this is what it's like in a sinner's heart.
Even, Gellical Underground Boat, Tour is on guam.
Yes, and then you all shoved youth masterbob off of the boat.
I still would have, it's a core childhood memory.
Yes.
But this is a kind of darkness you don't get outdoors at night.
Yeah, I mean, it's truly, truly dark.
No matter which way you look, you don't see anything.
Yeah, like you cannot see your hand in front of your face, literally.
Right.
And so that's a lot of what they're going through.
So these rights were performed in that kind of absolute darkness.
Right.
That's why you have torchbearers right as this
office, you have to lead people to the place and then put the torches out. Right? Like you have to
then re-light them to get them out. Right? So that darkness is, again, related to the underworld and death.
Interestingly, so Plato, when he talks about the Ellucidian mysteries, he says,
Oh, this is, sediciation is experience that brings about enlightenment.
and opens the news to the perception of the eternal and the higher things.
And so most modern scholars will be like,
oh, we'll see Plato reinterpreted the mysteries.
He gives of this new higher philosophical interpretation.
Blah, blah, blah.
And this is one of these fundamental errors.
and how we read today, especially in academia,
in that people aren't read as holes anymore.
WHOLES.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
That's right.
Like, you know, in the past, when you read Play-Doh,
you read like all of Play-Doh,
and you read all of Play-Doh in a particular order,
right?
Um, now no one does that?
Right, you get these bits and pieces on particular topics that usually that relate to whatever your particular discipline is that you're studying
So if you're doing philosophy if you're in a political science program, you know
You got these scraps of the Republican stuff and you know like and on laws, right
But there's you don't read the whole thing right and so
Let me suggest
That that is not a different interpretation
at all of what's going on in the mysteries.
because if you read some more Plato, you find out what Plato thinks happens when you die.
Yeah. And what what Plato thinks happens when you die is that your soul ascends
to the realm of forms, the realm of ideas, right, to the realm of the eternal,
and you behold these things, and then you get reincarnated.
Right? Your memories are washed away and you're reincarnated. But there are these latent
That's it.
of those eternal realities in your head so that learning is really a kind of
remembering for Plato. Yeah right right. And he demonstrates this at one point.
This is his demonstration. He says, I can get some slave boy and I can teach
of geometry by drawing with a stick of the sand.
a kid, especially a slave kid, can't understand geometry.
Ah, but see, because he could understand it, he's really remembering it from when his soul,
before he was reborn, beheld the perfect sphere.
It's said, stared at the orb briefly.
But so, yes, so Plato agrees.
Plato was saying, yes, this is experience of death and rebirth, which is what everyone
What else did I-
it was too, he just looks at death and rebirth a little differently than a lot of people.
But so in absolute darkness, the people were conducted to the edge of various, and I don't
know if it's precipices or precipices.
You got to write the first time.
precipices
Let up to the edge
of like cliffs and drops and pits and this kind of thing, right?
Again, to give you this experience of, of steady that you're an absolute darkness,
unsteadiness about to fall.
And it should be noted you are not sober.
Yeah, you have to, as I said, you have to imagine that some people did fall over.
Right?
They're, they're must have an accident that happened.
They're must have, but yes, they're probably were people who did not survive their
initiation. Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, that would just enhance the yeah, yeah, it was dangerous. That's right. Nice man. These mysteries are dangerous
Before they led you down into the darkness you were given a drink called Ka-ke-an
which
Technically just means a kind of like mold or spiced wine. Yeah
But
This was drugs.
This was spice like dune spice.
Yeah.
Here drink this.
When you get that in the mysteries, it's not just you're going to need to be hydrated
before your big experience.
So person is put into this altered state of consciousness, right?
Already by that then led in total abject darkness to points where they feel like they're
about to fall, they're about to die.
They're told they're being led into the underworld, right?
Okay.
And now the day new more of the mystery initiation. I think this is Father Andrew's favorite part.
Um, don't say that.
I didn't say why it's your favorite part.
No, it's not my favorite part. It's not my favorite part.
I'm not implying that you were initiated and this was your favorite part.
Not even a little bit.
Um, but so we're told
We're told by Athenagoras of Athens who is a late second early third century
Christian apologist who writes against various heresies and pagan religions.
The way this is generally translated into English, and we had this issue with
myth rest too. Last time the way it's translated in English is at the end of this.
Ritual after having all of these experiences in the darkness and an altered state of consciousness on the precipice of the abyss
They would display an ear of corn
It's very exciting
Yes, yes, this this this sounds like a fantastically anticlimactic
Look corn. Yeah, but I mean it should be noted of course like this is not corn like Americans think of corn
This is going like the British think of corn which just means
So it's a sheep of wheat or something.
Yeah.
Or barley or something, right?
But it's also not displayed because they're in darkness, right?
Yeah, it's not displayed.
There's a sort of a grass bag as it were.
Yes, so what they did, they'd have a basket.
A basket.
And the basket contained said ear of corn slash sheep of wheat.
I mean, do you like if you pick that out of the basket, considering as
as I'm about to mention the other options.
Do you win a prize or?
Oh no, you were supposed to feel the many things in the bass.
Oh, to get to, you were not selecting one.
Yeah, okay, okay.
Yes.
No.
So at the end of the, you're in this state,
you feel like you're about to fall into the,
they put your hand into this basket,
which contains this grain,
sheaf, right?
And also, and an assortment of fallacies,
various shapes and sizes.
Not my favorite part.
Should be said.
And so this is to make a connection,
right, the symbolic connection here is between sex
and reproduction and death and harvest and fertility.
Yeah, all of the same.
Which for an ancient pagan, like so for us,
we hear that and it's like, okay,
that is deeply weird, disturbing, gross.
Thank you for the parental advisory.
But for an ancient pagan, this...
I never trigger treating it that house again.
Right.
But for an ancient pagan, this all makes sense.
Like these things are all absolutely linked.
They don't think about these images the way that we do.
We think about the way in way do...
For two big reasons.
Number one, biggest version, Christianity.
Change the world.
Number two, also, you know, are sort of inherited
Victorian feelings about these things.
Yeah.
Remember everybody that ancient Rome is a place
you'd walk through the streets,
and there is very explicit pornography drawn
on many, many, many of the walls.
Like it is everywhere, all the time.
All the time, it is absolutely visible everywhere.
It is soaked in this stuff.
And this is one of the reasons why by the way,
we say that the ancient world is deeply,
deeply misogynistic.
You know, like, like, I'm not saying
that people aren't sinners in this particular way,
now, but by comparison, it's very, very tame. Obviously, it's still a sin to treat women
in this bad way. Obviously, it's still a sin. But the ancient world, it was horrible,
horrible. This thing we just mentioned shows, it's a symbol of the way that all of this
works. You know, it's just that there it is. There it is.
Yes, yes. So moving on from that, and again with the print
on advisory, it's going to get worse before it gets better.
I know hard to imagine, but it is.
Yeah. So we talked a little bit about some of the functionaries involved in this, in
in the sense of the torch spares, right?
But most of the functionaries, so there was a person who's kind of the high priest, the
hyrophant, right, and the high priestess, those were inherited offices within a particular
Athenian family, who held those priesthoods.
And the younger people, those families would make up the rest of the torchbearers and functionaries,
Right, in the sort of retinue beyond anybody who
was already initiated who came back to help.
But also there was a group that was sort of permanently attached to the shrine in Elliusus
who were called the Panahese.
Yeah, which by the way is the plural of Panahia.
Yes.
And they were women who were...
completely separated from men.
Yeah, so similar to the Vestal Virgins in Rome.
Yeah, I mean, the word itself, it means the all holy ones,
but it can also, but literally what it means
is the completely separated ones.
Because that's what holy means, separated, distinct,
set apart.
Yes, yes.
Yeah.
And so part of, but it interesting to note to take from this,
Right.
We are not in any way.
relating the Theotokos to...
No, the pagan priestesses.
No, no, no, no.
But just to say that that word, right,
is also a reference to her ever virginity.
Yeah, because she's completely set apart.
That title upon Aeia is a part of that,
completely set apart, not just at one point in her life
or up to one point in her life, but for her entire life.
Yeah.
So we move on.
All right.
Downward.
It gets, yes.
To the Dionysian mysteries.
I mean, you know this is going to be like the worst frat party ever.
Yes.
Depending on how you grade bested worst frat party.
I was never a member of a fraternity.
So there you are.
Yeah, I mean, I don't know how that works.
work. Yeah. I don't know. Yeah.
Yeah, we had an entire fraternity expelled from my college,
and the fraternity shut down after a party, sort of like this.
Um.
But not joke.
No, I was the guy.
That's the truth.
I was the guy that when certain fraternities,
including like honor fraternities,
would come and do events at the theater where I worked,
I was the guy who'd walk up to them and say,
you know, I think you're mistranslating your Greek motto here.
And they're always like, what?
Oh
would tell them, you know, and they're like, they just had no, I mean, God bless them, you
know, their theoretically is Greek life, but they do not read any Greek at all.
Yes.
That was minor action for turties.
The wildest thing about that for whole fraternity, getting kicked out of my college, all
at once, after throwing a ranger, was that there was one guy who took that semester off
for the fraternity.
So he came back the next semester and he was like the last man.
standing like he was the only he was the last of his kind yes he was the only one left just
because he was not in the state like at the time that it all went down so and through his
let me re-bought no yes do I try to rebuild what do I do right so all right that the so the the
the Dionysian mysteries.
Yes.
So there was this old theory.
So, and this is part of the, again, kind of dumb dumb justice league view of the Greek gods.
They're the 12 Olympians, right? And at a certain point, Dianis Didadis has shows up and
replaces one of them. Right? Like, Green Arrow just got too busy in his own comic, and so we had to
bring in a long-aided man, right? Like, to take his spot on the Justice League. Right? That's not
not how Greek religion ever worked at all.
Right.
And so we now know actually quite to the contrary that Dionysus in terms of the broad pagan
worship of Dionysus as a God goes way back in Greek history because we've found his name
in a linear B inscription.
Yeah, and linear B is like Proto-Greek.
The Earth.
Yeah, linear B is...
So, the spoken language was very clearly an early form of the same spoken language, but
linear B was written in a phonetic alphabet.
It's not kuneiform because it has a different symbolic system than kuneiform, but it's
like kuneiform in that each symbol represents a syllable.
Like in Japanese.
Right.
So to give you an example, right, the word for fruit is carposts.
Yeah.
in Greek in linear B it's two symbols, ca and pa.
Hmm. Got you.
Right. So you can trace roots and names of this, you could trace things back into linear B that way.
Right. And when you do Greek etymologies, we have a limited amount, we have sort of a library
of tablets with linear B inscriptions from no-sos mainly. That's pretty much all we have.
So there's a lot plenty of Greek words that aren't.
that aren't on any of those tablets.
Yeah, yeah.
Right, as far as we know.
So it's limitately useful in etymology.
But having studied a little bit of the year B
is how I disproved the word for mercy in Greek
as anything to do with the word for oil.
That's right, it doesn't.
It's a good pun.
So if you have shared that meme, shame on you.
and you go delete it right now.
slap your sleeve. I mean it makes a good
pun, but the one word is not derived from the other.
And talking about how mercy is like oil might be a nice, but there's literally no
etymological relationship. So both of those words, the word for olive oil,
let me go figure their Greeks, right? The word for olive oil, and the word for
mercy, both occur on linear B tablets that we have.
Yeah. Each of them is made up of two symbols.
It's not the same.
They have zero
symbols in common. Yeah. Yeah. They are not related words in any fashion. Yeah. Okay. So stop that.
And now back here, we're really scheduled mystery clothes. Yes. But so Dionysus, Dionysus's name is
is on, literally, as this is the name of a god, right? And so the broad pagan worship
it places where they had vineyards to make water.
to press wine, which is a lot of places in the Greek world.
They were worshipping Dionysus,
Bacchus in your Latin-speaking regions,
that were growing vineyards for wine.
This was the pagan god associated with that.
And so you have festivals for the Grey Parvist
and the making of new wine,
and all this kind of thing related to the worship of Dionysus
and a standard sense,
that's sort of the standard Dionysus cult.
sold.
So we're talking about the Dianistian mysteries though
You take the booze and the sex and the death and you you turn it up to 11
Essentially
In the case of the Dianistian mysteries so with the Elisinian mysteries
We know they were they were they were put in drugs. They were put in dope in the in the wine
But scholars argue over exactly what yeah
Yeah.
What exactly were they putting in there right?
Whereas with diadiscus we know hmm
because
Particularly in sites associated with the Diodesia mysteries diadiscus is depicted wearing reeds of
Poppies. Oh, well there you go
so
Opium
The real opiate of the masses. Yes
Essentially, the purpose of the D. N. I. C. and mysteries were to induce an altered state of consciousness.
This was true for everybody, so there's the broader festival, like the Bacchanalia, right, that's going on.
where this is going on low grade for everybody because everybody's getting drunk
probably a lot of the people are using drugs.
drugs, but the opium in particular, but the initiates are doing this on sort of this hardcore
level. So we've got the alcohol, we've got the opium, we have flagella, meaning whipsid
and it's that the people would whip and beat themselves.
So this is like if you're a burning man, like this is you...
You go to the freak tent, you know, like there's something going on over in that tent, you know, that's way beyond what everybody else is doing.
So there, and I mean, this isn't like, you know,
slap it yourself with your belt. These are like, skirches and stuff. So they're tearing up their backs, they're drawing blood.
Yeah. Right. This is to a pain to release endorphins.
Yeah, this is really, really tough.
We have these things like bull roars.
that they used to make this sort of droning noise,
this ongoing droning noise in the background, right?
While these people are working themselves up into this frenzy,
this drug at alcohol induced,
and Dorphan frenzy, at which point,
the issue of gauge in group sex.
So giant orgies happening, but that was at the climax.
The climax of the initiation was,
They would seize upon most...
rabbit and engage in homophagy that's the secret word for today kids which means eating a live animal.
Yeah so like well the thing about rabbits right is they're big enough to kind of tear into but
they're small enough you can really easily get hold of them like you wouldn't want to do this with
like a ball or a goat or something like yeah they're very very inconvenient but this is literally
tear into. It's a live animal. They're tearing it apart with their hands.
their teeth. I'm sure it seems much more reasonable after you've gone through all that other stuff.
Yes, once you're in that kind of bizarre frenzy, right, it culminates in this. Okay.
And so there is, and you'll see this in the both the iconographic depictions and the idols
of Dionysus and Pachis is that there's right the God.
And then there are the back A, right?
These other spirits, these sort of little minimes, right?
Of Dionysus and Bacchus, right?
And so the idea was sort of the general participants
in the festival were deliberately trying to
through the ultra-save consciousness
be possessed by these spirits.
Right? This wasn't seen as just a frenzy as in like,
oh, I'm all wound up.
This one.
seen as you're being possessed by this spiritual being and driven to this kind of what they consider divine friends
a the initiates it was sort of back as a dynasties himself
uh sort of the presider at the feast and and connected to the feast where the initiation
took place you had the temporary overturning of the social order yeah which
right. So it slaves being crowned and yeah like like this is
And it's interesting that this kind of even survives this idea, this particular piece of it,
not all of it, survives into like medieval Europe where you get the practice known as
twelfth night, which of course is carnival practices. Yeah, carnival practices. Again, you know,
of course, there's the very famous Shakespeare play twelfth night. And part of what's twelfth
night is the night before Epiphany, so it's it's January 5th. And often you would have, as you said,
the up.
upending the social order.
So the servants would be made, you know, the lords of the castle.
And then the lords would be, would act like slaves.
And you know, and there would often be this figure
called the Lord of Misrule, who's kind of put in charge
for the night, you know.
But yeah, it's this, it's this kind of upside down world
sort of thing that they're doing.
Yeah, yeah.
Of course, this would also, you've got the whole group sex
element.
You've got people swapping genders, people, yeah.
Yeah
the gender swapping is sort of done in 12th and 12th.
Yeah, you know, not exactly.
It's just disguise.
It's just see this is what happens.
Well, a lot of that is just that as I say,
this was happened with Christianity.
It gets a hold of some of this stuff.
It just wipes out all of the super problematic stuff
and just kind of keeps a very,
I don't know.
As we've said, as we've said on the great tales,
like fairy tales are kind of what's left over
when Christians really work
over mythology. You know? Well, you get his fairy tales, right? And so this is, you know,
like 12th night is kind of the fairy tale version of this horrifying thing that we're talking
about. Yes. Yes. Of Devil's Night. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And also part of that, you have to remember,
is that to the English psyche, there is nothing funnier than a man performatively dressed as a woman.
Right? I mean witness Betty Hill and my-
anti-python. Right. I mean, this, this, yeah, exactly. It meant something very different
in like the medieval Renaissance period and how it would be received. So in this case,
right, we talked about how in the Ellucinian mysteries, right, there's this experience,
you're sort of sharing in the experience of Persephone in the underworld and all this, right?
Anyway, we're saying, so when you do all that to yourself and go into this crazed frenzy and
you know yeah what's the story that you're just had sex with
people and now you're tearing into a live rabbit after beating yourself bloody and doing drugs
and booze. What experience is that participating in? Well, diet, I was gonna say, of these
nature loving kind pagans that we've heard so much about since the 1970s. Yes. You are participating
in diet and ice-sizzling own experience of having been torn into pieces boiled in milk and
mm-hmm
There we go.
So there you go.
Yeah.
Procible, similar ritual behind do not eat a kid boiled in its mother's milk.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, and of course the thing that's similar here to other stuff that we've looked at is
like there's this element of dying going to the underworld sort of coming back.
you know, all of this because again, this is one of these common things is there this catholic element
Right to all this right. Yeah, it's just the de-disc inversion is particularly violent. Yeah, yeah
Yeah, now
Top of everything else now. Let's talk about what I think is
The worst of the examples of this. Oh, is this your favorite part? No, this is my
I do not cast favor upon this part father Steven
I said
There's nothing but disfavor.
Nothing but disfavor.
Fully merit a disfavor.
So we've talked about kind of the big ones, right,
in terms of mystery cults, right?
The big famous ones, right?
But there are also lots of little local variations
and smaller mystery cults.
And some of them even get deliberately created
at certain periods in time.
Some of them pretend
that they're completely ancient, right?
But others don't, right?
And so we're gonna talk about one of the more interesting ones.
We gotta warn the Brits here,
you're gonna have far less appreciation
for a certain wall after hearing about this.
It might be a little triggering.
Whereas a lot of Jewish people who hear this
will be like, we were right all along, right?
Indeed.
this guy.
And we're going to talk about the Emperor Hadrian.
Roman Emperor Hadrian.
The wall guy, again, if you're the guy who built the wall, which I've been to.
Just recently I went to Hadrian's wall.
I did not go underground.
The guy who was responsible for a lot of the rebuilding of what had been Jerusalem as
is Ali a capitalina featuring a big statue of himself on a pillar.
As one does, one is Roman Emperor.
Yes, so he's the one who put down the Barcocque Verbalion in Palestine at the time, the Roman
Provence of Palestine. But we're particularly talking about him here in this mystery cult context
in terms of his favorite, speaking of favorite,
for a period of his life, Antonyus.
So, the upper Hadrian was a petarast.
I mean, as a lot of elite Romans at the time were.
Yes, right?
Engricks.
Yes.
But so he and favorite is the word that Roman writers used to refer to the
teenage boy who was Hadrian's sexual partner at any given point in time. That was his favorite.
Yeah. I told you it was going to go downhill even more than it already had. Yep. So you're
warned. Yeah. Prital advisories very much still in effect. So Antony's was from was a guy
from Bethinia when he was about 13. He was sent to Rome to study and that's where the emperor
took a shine to him, I guess, and made him his new favorite around the time he was 14 or 15.
Then when he was 19, shortly before his 20th birthday, Antony was died.
And Hadrian, being the Roman emperor, as one does, decided that his dead...
lover and lover is being polite about it, his dead victim had become a God. Yeah, it
just didn't usually go that way. Yeah, even a messed up situation that happened over
over. So this is a, yes, this is a mystery cult founded on Peter Astey. Yeah. And so
So Hadrian starts building temples to have him worshiped as a God.
It's some of the Greek places where we found worship of it.
He was considered a hero, not a god per se.
Yeah, so a sort of a semi-divine figure like that.
Yes, Greeks trying to split the difference.
Right.
Yeah, yeah.
But so Hadrian, and we know this was all over the place because we have 20 some odd temples
to Antony's.
Yeah.
and wildly different parts of the Roman Empire than Hadrian.
built. So this is a thing that he was serious about and that kind of took off. And part of this was he
also established a mystery cult. Hadrian himself had taken Antonyus with him to go and be initiated in the
the Ellucinian mysteries that we talked about earlier, and he basically modeled the
Antononian mysteries after.
that was sort of a rip off, right? Part of this was he built a cultic center for the worship of his
dead victim. He had named it Antidoopolis. The city of
Antidoopolis. Yes, right. Which was, there wasn't really a border at this time in history, but
But the transitional region between upper and lower Egypt, along the
Nile, he built this city, not on a rock and roll. He just built this city. And there he built
the central temple in the city was the temple to Antony's Osiris, which means that he's kind of
assimilating them to each other. And of course Osiris, if you know anything about Egyptian mythology,
you might know that Osiris part of his story is that he dies, gets dismembered.
and then comes back sort of kind of,
there's a whole issue with his phallus.
Right, right.
Just to tie all the themes together.
Yeah.
Yeah, and so, yes, he's saying by this
that Antidus, his dead victim,
was an embodiment of the Egyptian goddess Iris.
Yeah, sort of a hippostasis honor, basically.
Yes.
Now, even though that's what he did in Egypt,
Most of
what we have, he was actually trying to assimilate and say that his dead victim was an embodiment
of hermys. That's mostly in the West. In the East more commonly, he gets assimilated
with Dionysus. And what we mean by assimilate here, when we say this, what we really mean
is sometimes this is done verbally, like the temple of
and to do some service.
But a lot of what we're talking about is in iconography.
It's in religious iconography.
So it's antitrust being portrayed as
Hermes or as Dionysus or as Osiris.
In terms of how he's dressed, how he's portrayed,
the other symbolism in the imagery.
Right? And you can see how all these other mystery cults
are touching on this.
And we have, when I say iconography,
I mean, we have bar reliefs.
We have a
bunch of statuary. Oh yeah. And there's a bunch of surviving statues of
Yeah, and you can look by the way, I mean, there is a lengthy wiki pidi article about this young man.
And you can see the statues in the article and there's even, you know, a medallion and all,
I mean, there's all kinds of stuff connected with this. I mean, it goes on and on and on.
Yeah, and so one of these there's a bust of antonus
Hermes. Uh, that's in a museum now, uh, in Russia, because it came for the private collection
of one, Catherine, the great. Yeah. Yep. So see this even ties into holy Russia. There
you go. We're talking about Catherine, the great holy is in quotation marks. Um, she wasn't
that great. It's kind of the, it's kind of the rule of, of Russian imperial history, you
know, that, that the rulers that are styled the great were not so great and the ones, you
the terrible were actually not that terrible.
Yes.
So, Antidopolis was famous for one other thing,
and that is that not long after that city was founded
and probably relatedly to why it was founded
in the Central Temple and everything,
it became a hub of Egyptian magic,
of sort of assimilated Egyptian and Hellenistic magic.
And when I say magic, obviously I'm talking about, we've talked about it before, magic
in the ancient pagan context.
We did a whole episode on this called Sores and Sorcery, Mostly Sorcery.
Yeah.
So, on what, you know, how magic was worked in the ancient world.
But this was considered to be a particularly dark and rotten type of magic, even by pagans.
Yeah, like, like, black magic.
Black magic.
Yes.
like the bad stuff. This is Domest with the Voodoo. This was right. All the worst forms of hermedicism,
which by the way gets its name from Hermes. So as I just said what's interesting is we have,
as you might expect, given when this happens in the second century, and we have a lot of Christian
Apologists and anti-heretical writers writing in the second and third centuries.
or a fair number at least. There are a lot of Christian denunciations of this. Yeah. I mean,
yeah. As one might imagine, like, yeah, as one might imagine, like this stuff is going on,
it's this is terrible. Don't go there. This is awful. This is the worst. And so there's there's
three main counts on which this gets denounced. This is probably intuitive. You could probably
guess these one is obviously the anti-pagan level of
like hermys and everything.
Yeah.
What is the anti-peterasti level?
And then one is the anti-evil magic level.
And remember, this is not like satanic panic,
Christians going around looking for stuff
to get really unhappy about.
This is the norm throughout culture.
Yes, right. These are Christians responding
Pastorially to what's actually going on in the culture. Yes, right? This is like the book of Acts, right they come
They bring the gospel to the tanner who's bringing out their magic books and burning them. Yeah, yeah
Right, so there it has it now
That you would probably expect what you might not expect is that we also have tons of pagan denunciations
Yeah, I mean, I'm always interested kind of in in
and pagan denunciations of other paganism.
Like when pagans are like, no, this,
this just goes too far.
Yes, this is just way too far.
So, and a lot of it was like, you know,
the Romans had a real issue.
We're really sensitive to emperors going insane.
It's kind of a problem.
Yes, it's a thing that happened, right?
Not infrequently, right?
What's the possibility?
Yes.
It had very bad consequences even for your run of the Mill pagan Roman, right?
So this was a bad the mad emperor was a bad thing all around and so
I think a lot of the pagan just the issues are this is
exhibit a
Considered by them, you know, you're your dead
Erasties being proclaimed a god and you're building temples over the empire to him
this was considered sort of exhibit a of
of Hadrian Dunlost is my
right? Like, but so they talk about the whole black magic element which is interesting, right?
And they're opposed to black magic of course because they believe it works. Right. Right. I mean
they're not anti-magic exactly. It's like no no this is just too dark and too weird and too
whatever. Yes. Yes. This is like your local witch and or local psychic or local pulmonary or
you not to mess with Ouija board.
Right, right.
Right.
Right, like, you know, the Christians and the pagans are telling you the same thing, probably
good advice.
But to give you an idea about why it spread this was, even our old friend Kelsus or
Celcus.
Yeah.
Right.
The guy who, the critic of Christianity, the pagan who attacked Christianity, was considered
the greatest attack on Christianity that origin responded to.
Second century.
Even he went after them.
Yeah.
Well, it's still a big-
What's wild is the basis on which he did that?
Yes, yes, so what's amazing is Kelsus hates this form of paganism
Hates Christianity, so how does he denounce this form of paganism?
Taking a dead man and making him out to be a god is is Christian garbage. This is Christian mumbo jumbo
Yeah
So the pagancy doesn't like as a pagan or the
Pagan's who are look a little too much like Christianity to him.
I'm just shaking my head. I can't put that on the air, but I'm shaking my head.
Yeah.
It's just kind of amazing. And what's crazy?
And I mean, like Christianity to arrangement syndrome. Yeah.
Right. Right. He's so he's so he's so flummoxed by Christianity that he
starts calling this stuff.
Christianish, whatever. And what's amazing, one of the things that's amazing.
I mean this is all amazing and not in a good way.
way to me is that there are actually people here in 2025.
I can't believe this is an amazing to me.
This is expected to be.
Yeah, it is.
It is.
I guess I just live in a perpetrator.
Of course.
Is that there are people here in 2025 who are trying
in some way to bring back the Antuninian or whatever you call
Antuninian mysteries because they think that this in some way
represents.
You know, like consensual homosexuality or something like this.
Yes.
This is somehow spiritualized or divine or sacred homosexuality.
It's just whatever you think of homosexuality.
It's just not.
This is an emperor.
An emperor taking a teenage boy.
Okay.
And that's the basis of this religious practice.
Like, yes.
Okay.
All right.
Well, now that we're-
I would think were you a homosexual person,
you would want to denounce this
and associate yourself with?
Right, right.
But for some not.
I guess not.
For some.
Lots of people want to larp.
Apparently if you're gay and you want to do the
Dio pagan larp thing,
I mean, for some of this is it.
There it is.
So now that we've descended down into these...
We're going to take our second foul break for this episode and we'll be right back with God willing something a little bit better.
how did
the sun cross once carried by the pagans of the Baltic North, become the cross of Jesus.
How did the last pagan nation of medieval Europe first encounter Christ in the Orthodox
Church?
Herodotus said these people were known the swirfs.
Con with Azazala Pilgrim is through the sometimes strange, sometimes surprising history of
the Dwaynean.
to land poised between peace and west.
Hey, welcome back everybody.
It's the third half of this truly astonishing episode
of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Hills to Estonish.
Yeah, why, okay, why are we talking about all this?
Well, number one, of course,
this is the kind of thing we talk about
on this wacky podcast of ours.
See, you guys thought we didn't have anything interesting
left in us after five plus years.
Here we are throwing this at you.
But more importantly than that,
there are people who argue
that Christianity is derived from this,
which of course is what we were talking about
to some extent last time.
you know people say that christian is
to arrive from myth-raism and we showed how that is just utter bunk.
But there are people who say that Christianity is a kind of mystery cult and that it has
its basis in all of this stuff.
And so like, okay, well, let's look at what the actual content of all of those things
is.
So now having heard all that, is it the case?
Is there any basis for this?
Why do people say that Christianity isn't some way derived from the...
these mystery calls from ancient world.
What's the best we could do with that argument?
Yeah, what is the steel man of that argument?
So to say that's right, if there could be one,
more like a tin man in this case, but aluminum man,
at least not straw.
Yeah, well yeah, and this is, so by the way, right,
just to let you a little bit into the madness
in my methods.
right? This is sort of the negative argument to the positive argument of religion of the apostles.
Yeah. Right? When I make arguments that Christianity is right, the fulfillment of Judaism that
Christianity comes out of second-templed Jewish traditions, it's as opposed to the folks out there
who want to argue that it comes from pagan traditions.
So part of how I make the
that overall argument, part of how we make that argument
on this show, right, is to show how Christianity flows from
Jewish traditions.
The other half is on the negative side,
showing the radical disconnect and discontinuity
between Christianity and pagan religions.
Yeah.
Yeah. Which is what we're seeing tonight.
Right.
That's the purpose of all this grossness.
Yep.
the giddy delight I get in.
being transgressive. It is that, but it's not only that. Right. It's also right to show
this stark contrast between what's going on in a mystery cult and what's going on in Christianity.
Right. But so what's the best we could say if you want to try and find connections and
you're going to find just like with mythorism, we have to get kind of vague. Right. Yeah.
So probably an obvious place to start is that...
Like early, for instance, we know that in early Christian practice that the Eucharist was,
was private, you know, people would not be sent out.
Like we still have this liturgy, right?
We'd dismiss Catecumans, at least the prayers are said, even if Catecumans are not actually
sent from the room.
Yeah.
So there's that sense of like, okay, only certain people can participate in this part, you know.
Right.
prayer before receiving you
Chris right now not speak of that mystery sign enemies right
So right you could point at that you could point at that. Say see. Huh only the initiated were allowed into the
You just not really a parallel
You know vaguely right okay, what did that?
You could you could point at baptism as an initiation ritual right with just that there's lots of initiation rituals
Yeah, it's got it's got death and rebirth in it. So hey right but there death and resurrection
Right? So there's kind of something.
Right? Yeah.
This initiation ritual.
Vagely, kind of something.
There's this idea of participation in like the elements
of the life of Christ.
Right? Your baptized into his death, right?
You're sharing this spirit, Christ is a divine figure.
is a divine figure, right? Like...
We're being vague, but, you know, our
POSCO liturgics are very much, you know,
darkness and light passing from death
to resurrection, death to life, right?
There's some of that, literally going on, yeah?
If we're vague, right?
But there's the big butt.
So there's the best, kind of the best we could do
in terms of continuities.
Now some discount newities.
Aside from all the obvious ones with sex and eating live animals and all that, had drugs.
But possibly an even more core level, right?
At a more core level in Christian liturgics, and any of the specific examples we gave
included, right?
The experience is not the thing.
Yeah.
it's really important to underline this that historic Christianity is not...
about having a spiritual experience.
Like no one cares.
Richially speaking, just good,
because no one cares what you feel.
If you feel anything at all.
It's good news for me,
because I have no feelings.
There we go.
But I too can be a Christian.
Even the touch can be safe.
Yes.
Right.
It doesn't matter.
A Dutch Gen X or even.
It doesn't matter if you feel it.
I mean,
If you have feelings, we're not saying it's bad to have feelings.
If you have feelings, if you're having some kind of spiritual experience, whatever that might be,
that's nice. That could, that can be nice, but it's not critical. It's not the goal. It's not
required. And I think one of the things that one of the practices that really underlines this
for Christianity and just shows how the idea that that spiritual experience is not the goal,
how that's really important.
here is that we have babies participating in core rituals of our faith. We baptize them,
we commune them. You know before any of that happens we bring them in, we church them
and you know what are they experiencing? Like there's no point where they're going to go oh yes
I had this big initiation experience. Nothing they consciously remember. Right, right. There's nothing
Whereas if experience was the goal, then we would make them wait.
We would make them wait for baptism. We would make them wait for communion.
You had to be one of the prerequisites to be initiated into these mysteries is you had to be
a person who was seen culturally and everything as being capable of having that experience.
Yeah, there's no slaves were not initiated because there are scenes being like children
Yeah, yeah, so there's no minimum age in Christian story Christianity to experience the core rituals
It was like adult-free men
Considered capable of this whereas in Christianity slaves are welcome in babies are welcome in
Women are welcome in even even low-class women in like
Everybody's welcome in in Christianity. You don't have to put it that way. I mean, I'm just saying class women
Wow, I mean, I'm just saying like,
probably some of these mysteries, it will be only women of the upper classes, the upper
class. No, I know. Yeah, yeah. You know what I meant.
They're like working class, working, working class. But you know what I mean, like, like,
you don't have to be some kind of, you don't have to be some kind of cultural elite to participate
in Christianity. I think Christian women are very classy. That's all I say. Absolutely.
Of course they are.
That's...
Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah.
And people, this is a term that people should learn
if you don't already know it, and that's epiphenomena.
Yeah.
So you have a phenomena, you have a thing, right?
Sorry, I have to, you say every time you say phenomena,
and I have to, in my head.
Okay.
And you have a thing, and then there are other things
which often accompany it, and the things which often accompany
it are epiphenomenal.
Yeah.
Okay.
So.
So for us and for historic Christianity, spiritual experience is epiphenomenal.
It's something that often happens, not required, but is not the thing itself.
So if you are baptized, let's say you're baptized as an adult.
You're baptized as an adult.
may have some kind of profound spiritual experience when that happens.
when you're chrismated, received however you received into the church. You may have some
profound and often people do have a profound kind of spiritual experience in that. But if
you don't, that doesn't mean it didn't happen. Which I think or didn't work. I think it's
really important to point this out because every so often, you will see photographs that
get circulated on the internet, where someone is getting baptized or chrismated or something
I'm sorry.
happening. And you'll see, you know, uh, lights or whatever. And now I'm not saying that
that stuff is not real, although sometimes, sometimes it is lens flare, boys and girls,
sometimes it is. Orbs, we saw orbs on the video. It's ghosts. You know, but let's say,
let's say that that flashing lights really did happen. Let's say there is some kind of
whatever. That is epiphenomenal. Like if you open up the book, the liturgical book,
that the priests have. There is nowhere in there it says, and if this is real, then you will see
lights. It never ever ever says that, never says that. And so to use that as some kind of proof
of your position on this or that controversy within the church is very dangerous, very, very
dangerous. Not only because of the whole lens flare thing, although I mean we have to accept that
That's entirely possible.
But let's say it really is truly a miraculous thing
that you're seeing, interpreting it
to fit your particular ideology about a controversial issue
suggests that there needs to be some kind
of spectacular experience going on
in order for something to be real.
And that is not Christianity.
It's not.
Yes.
That's an easy way to follow the spiritual delusion.
Absolutely.
Because that's what demons can do.
They can cause you to see lights.
Yeah.
I'm not saying that those lights in the photos are demon, you know, or have demon origins,
but, but stop it, people.
Stop it.
Again, what does it say in the book?
What does it say in the canons?
What does it say in the scriptures?
What does it say in the traditional sources?
Stop adding these things on top of it as your authenticators.
Yes.
Also, Tom Hanks is opinion on this, does not matter.
Have you heard that he's orthodox?
I heard these orthodox.
Did you know that?
Yeah, I heard that too.
Did I tell you about my last profound spiritual experience?
Did it involve Tom Hanks?
No.
Oh, okay.
So, this is a rare window into the fevered processes of my mind.
Ooh.
Let's hope they cut this one.
I'll-
I want them to cut this one for a short on the YouTube's.
Yeah, yeah.
So this is during the bad times of 2020.
Oh, yeah.
And I was serving Mattins by myself.
Yep, we all did that.
And I just finished the beginning part,
and I made the sign of the cross with the sensor
over the gospel book, right?
And I put the sensor back, and I'm standing there,
I'm doing the...
doing the prayers. And I see in my vision, I see, you know, like a ripple, like there's still incense smoke rising from the altar.
And I said, wow, this is profound. And I started to smell something. And I kind of got accurate.
And I looked down and I had set the sleeve of my jibbion with the sensor while I was blessing the gospel.
worst nightmare right there. So don't jump to the conclusion that it's necessarily a spiritual
experience. I mean, that's, and that's worse than just getting kid be unusually. Yes.
Which is a professional hazard for us in the anti-aconurge test. It was, it was actually the
lining. And so like the lining, there's like a burning ring expanding outward, right? Like the orange,
Like, you could burn in ring of fire.
Cross the lighting.
Yes. I went down, down, down and the flames went higher.
Yeah. Take it for me, kids. Preleous disease.
The. So yeah, so that's a big issue. That's a major issue. That the experience is not the thing
in anything we do, right? When you receive the Eucharist, whether you have some kind of feeling or
experience or not.
you have still received Christ, period, full stop. It happened. When you're
received to the church whether you feel something or not or what you feel you've
been received into the church, it's done. It's happened. Also, yeah, you know,
So the Eucharist is members only, right?
But this is not an individual.
None of these even baptism or a christmas reception of the church.
None of these things are individual rights.
Yeah, even if it's as often happens these days, it's just like just the family attending
or whatever, which it really, really it should be the community doing this together.
I try desperately to avoid doing that.
Sometimes it happens.
But even then it's still a community thing.
still the you know the churches do
doing this. And ideally, actually, groups of people are being baptized all together.
That's what the rubrics, the liturgics really are kind of assuming in many cases, is that
you've got a number of people being baptized.
But even if for some reason, it was during the dark times of 2020, and you got baptized
or chrisimated, you were the only person there, right? What you were initiated into was a
persistent community.
That's right.
not you are now a ma-
of a community, the misrecotes did not do that.
It's not a higher state of consciousness or knowledge
or any of that kind of stuff.
Individual basis.
Yeah.
Which I mean, honestly, sometimes people act
like Orthodox Christianity is that.
Like you can see this especially on the interwebs,
you know, this sense of like,
well, you just haven't read the blah, blah, blah,
or you know, all this kind of stuff.
Yeah, no, no, no.
It's a worshiping community.
That's a dangerous secrets contained in the philicalia.
Dun dun dun dun.
Yes.
I mean, this is why we call, this is why we,
from the beginning, call each other brother and sister.
Yeah.
There's this familiar language.
By the way, the whole philicalia thing, right?
I know this is a meme in some circles to talk.
Oh, there are things in there that are dangerous.
You should not read it, or that consultative nurse
for the love.
OK, the problem is not that there's
something you're going to read in there that's
to make your brain explode or something.
No, I've read it all right or hidden knowledge the problem is some of us are dumb enough to try and take that stuff and apply it to ourselves
right
In inappropriate ways and inappropriate times. That's why you have to talk to your spiritual father about it right
It's not that it's something the stages to be read. It's what you're liable to do with it
That's potentially the problem and that's not just a problem with the philicalia
Yeah, that's a problem with the rudder.
That's a problem.
A lot of the church fathers writings.
Yeah.
Right.
Like, it's probably scripture, frankly.
You can read scripture and apply it to yourself in dumb ways, right?
Like, you could set yourself on fire.
I think you're having a spiritual experience, right?
This stuff happens.
So there's also a big problem when we talk about, right, yeah,
the Eucharist is celebrated and private and its members only.
but Christians go out and try to get.
other people to become members. Yeah, we like for us, the idea that some people can't
commune is, you know, a problem to be solved. Right? It's not what you bring you into communion.
Yeah, it's not a feature, you know, we want everybody being communion. We want the whole world
in the church. Every single human person is invited into the church. It is openly proclaimed.
This is this is the
sense of the gospel that it's an open proclamation. There's nothing kind of esoteric about it.
Yeah, this is for absolutely everyone. Again, we let babies in.
This is for everyone everyone. And there's not two different christianities. There's not like
Christianity for the Huy Palloy and Christianity for the elite. Oh yeah. Right? Yeah.
And part of that is because there's not an elite. Yeah. Contra what some people seem to think.
Right.
there's just Christians, right? And I know you may be thinking of Dostosism, we're going to get there.
Right? But it's important to note here, and this is something I've said before, probably on the air
before, that people don't like. And that's that when you go into some kind of quasi-orthodox
fundamentalist situation or rigorous situation, you basically end up verging into
On a whole bunch of counts.
And one of those is this and you tend to see this among
That unbalanced quasi orthodox group.
Some of them are members of quasi orthodox groups
That make a big deal about insisting to you how true and genuine they are, for example.
Yes.
If you have to say that, it's probably not true.
Yep.
That's sort of the equivalent of, I don't want to be blank, but that means you're blank,
right?
So if you're saying true or genuine, you're not.
But anyway, who have some individual or small group of contemporary elders who are basically
treated as this kind of spiritual elite, who understand all these things better than any
Many of us mere mortals could possibly fathom.
Right. And that's, you know, that's narcissism. But we'll talk more about that in a couple
of minutes. So what then? If it's so clear, and I think it is pretty clear, hopefully it's
pretty clear to you by this point, that there's no real connection other than antithesis between
Christianity and pagan mystery cults.
What do we do with
the Greek terminology, the Greek language of mystery and mystery cultic language that shows up, for example, in the New Testament, which is a thing.
It's true. That language is bad.
Yeah, or the fact that, for instance, our sacraments, we call them holy mysteries.
Yeah, I mean, we often want to kind of inflate stuff, especially spiritual stuff.
off but I think a good
to begin is what does the word itself mean? The basic sense of the word mystery,
misdidion, it just means a thing that's hidden, a thing that's hidden. Yes. Right?
And usually the context of that thing having been hidden being later revealed.
Right, especially in Christianity. And that's not... Well, but that's not... I mean,
that's not just a core element. Back in ancient Greek usage. Like, think about a
mystery now.
novel. Yeah, yeah, it's about, you know, revealing there is some secret something that is unknown
and then by the end of the novel is revealed. Yeah, I wouldn't be a very good mystery novel
right. If it never revealed like, oh, I never found out who killed the guy. Yeah, just
we'll never know. That would be kind of a lame, lame novel. Right, right. So that idea
that eventually it is revealed to someone somehow.
Right.
Is, is kind of.
of also there. That's true in the mystery called too. Yes, there's this secret stuff, but
there are initiates who have experienced the secret stuff. It's not still mysterious
to them. This is probably one of the most common usage of the language of mystery in the
the new testament, right? So you have...
The mystery, and various mysteries, right, that were mysterious in the Old Testament in
previous times, and then in the person of Christ they are now revealed.
They are revealed first by him to his disciples and then through his disciples to the world.
Yeah.
Mystery solved that.
Right.
So that's the most common thing going on with the mystery language.
Okay?
Not and again we're going to talk about nosticism right not Christ had these secrets you know
He had the stuff he told everybody, but then he had these other secrets
Then he only told his inner circle and we're the guys who still have those right gospel of Thomas
Yeah, that's not historical Christianity right that's something else that is more like the mystery cults, but that's something else
and
We also have initiation, and initiation rituals and baptism in particular in the New Testament, talked about, again, not in terms of, oh now you have personally had this experience, but in terms of you are now a part of this living community, ongoing community.
Right, you have now entered into the church.
The New Testament talks about the church a lot.
Hmm, a lot.
So if you see somebody from a Christian tradition online who talks a lot about the Bible and you never hear them really talking about the church, this should cause you to think and cause you to wonder.
And also we have to take into account that the New Testament and some of the early fathers are directly addressing a pagan audience or a formerly pagan audience.
They're addressing a pagan audience with the
gospel or they're trying to teach and explain the Christian faith in the Christian way of life to
former pagans. Right? And so when you're doing that, you're going to use their language sometimes to
try to communicate with them. Yeah, I mean, this is like when St. Paul's on the
New York, I guess, and he says, you know, I saw you guys had this alter to this unknown God and I
proclaim him to you. Now if you take that in the most absolute literal way
possible, then then then you have to read, say, Paul is saying, this demon that you are
worshiping is the demon that I'm proclaiming to you. Because there's no way.
Okay. Sacrifices you could offer it. You are really offering to the Jewish God. Yeah. Or
yeah. That or or like all the pigs you are. Yeah. You know that the religious practices surrounding
that altar to known, known God were Greek pagan practices.
So if you read them out.
literally and absolutely then he's endorsing that on some level. But that is not what he means.
He's using the religious language and imagery that they know in order to launch into, if you read
in there and X, it was at 17, to launch into a point by point takedown of all the basic metaphysics
of all of paganism actually. But he's using that language in order to communicate with them.
Right right and
Climate of Alexandria does the same thing
Right, it is addressed to the Greeks
Greeks doesn't mean ethnically Greek people Greeks when used by early church fathers means pagans
Yeah, they were still pagans around they just called them the Greeks right
that's
and
So he uses all kinds of mystery cult and other pagan terms in that to try to explain Christianity to them and
Yeah.
And this is one of the great problems in bad hermeneutics all over the place in our
modern day discourse.
Yeah.
Because what do people say about Clement of Alexandria when they talk about him at all?
Often he's used to kind of semi rehabilitate origin because they're sort of like you think
origin was bad with the pagan philosophy stuff.
Reclimate of Alexandria.
Right.
And his blanket assumed that because he uses these terms, what he means by those terms is the pagan concepts.
Yeah.
Right.
Another example.
Our Protestant friends, a lot of the way they go wrong in reading the New Testament, is because they're using what they call grammatical historical exegesis,
majoring in the grammatical part, which means they're reading each Greek word.
in the New Testament and wanting to interpret it according to its pagan Roman usage.
That's how you end up with all this quote unquote forensic or penal language supposedly in
the New Testament is because you're reading in terms of the pagan meaning, right?
What's the alternative?
The alternative is St. Paul is expressing Hebray, Hebrew and Aramaic concepts, Jewish concepts
in the Greek language.
So
What you'd want to do is, for example, hey, this Greek word that St. Paul uses, what Hebrew word is that used to translate in the Old Testament?
If I go and look at the Greek translation of the Old Testament.
Oh, so in St. Paul uses this Greek word, he means this Hebrew concept.
Yeah, it turns out that, you know, to put it in a brief way, he's speaking Septuagint, so to speak.
Yes, you know, right? He's he's
speaking Hebrew and Aramaic in Greek as are the other New Testament writers.
Yeah. Right?
Say, Clement of Alexandria, if he goes back and forth whether he's a saint or not.
Yeah. Okay. I'm not ruling on this. I'm just saying I've seen sources, some of which
say he is an Orthodox state and some of which say he technically isn't. So half the time
I call him, say, Clement of Alexandria and half the time I don't, I am thereby reflecting
the tradition accurately.
Um, right? He's not.
using these pagan words and concepts with their pagan meaning. He is expressing Christian
concepts using that language, and so you need to get to the Christian concept.
Saint Augustine is read incorrectly by almost everyone because they assume he's writing
and Latin because he only knew Latin, right?
But what he's do-
is he is for the first major time I might add. This is part of why Satan
Gusted was a genius, right? Despite whatever quibbles you may have with
this theology, most of which are fake because it's not an accurate representation of
his theology. But right, he's for the first time expressing these first serious
time, expressing these concepts that had previously been discussed and hammered
out in Greek. Right?
He's expressing those Christian ideas in Latin,
meaning he's taking Latin words
and turning them into technical terms,
all over the place.
Yeah.
And so you can't read St. Augustine and assume
that by a given Latin word, he means
it's general Latin usage at the time.
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean, I think
I'm a specific Christian concept.
Yeah.
A great, I mean, I think we've,
I'm pretty sure we've endorsed the book
on this show before,
Bye bye.
Just in case, because it's really relevant at this moment,
if you're really interested in the way that Christianity takes classical culture
and language and so forth and repurposes it for its own purposes,
Yaroslav Pelikin's book, Christianity and classical culture,
is the sort of magisterial work on this.
Like it is the one that really goes into all of the detail.
But I mean, you know, like this kind of thing happens even now with stuff from much later.
Right? For instance, in the, you know, 16th, 17th, 18th, 19th century, particularly, you get...
Which are all centuries I do my best to ignore.
Right. You know, in the history of the world.
In this period, in the early modern period, right, you get a number of Orthodox saints who, especially
look at where they are geographically, right? They are
speaking to
Latinate
Cultures cultures that are there the culture is formed by Roman Catholicism some cases the cultures formed by Protestantism
But mostly Roman Catholicism based on where they are
And the education they receive and the education they received absolutely
um and
They're using that terminology
In order to express the Orthodox faith
And there are people who are misreading them.
using that terminology and importing, frankly, the non-orthodox meanings of those words and reading
the church fathers as teaching, frankly, either Roman Catholicism or Protestantism in one way or
another, the early modern Orthodox church fathers, rather than looking at how they are embedded
within the Orthodox tradition. And you can always tell when people do this, because when they're giving
they're big, you know, the
big meme quotes, like look at my meme, I made, look at this meme, I made, look at this
meme, I made, and they just dump these quotes from these church fathers.
It's a wall of text in a picture or whatever.
Yeah, it's a massive wall of text in a picture.
And then if you look at the dates and the locations, they're all kind of clustered together
in time and space.
That's not how the Orthodox tradition works.
Right?
So if you isolate that stuff and then say, well, this is this.
often interpreted in ways that the early church would never have heard of.
Um, then you're getting wrong.
You're getting it wrong.
Some of some of these dunces when they post that wall of text,
if you actually read it, it, it says the opposite of what they claim.
Yes.
Right.
That is often the case.
Even on the surface in English.
Yes.
Right.
Yeah.
Like so, you know, I don't want to give too much credit to these folks,
but even the more astute of them, right, even the more astute of them.
And this is more some, some more rent free living for many.
But
are just assuming that if an 18th century Russian saint uses a Latin theological term,
they mean by it, what the Latin's mean by it.
Yeah.
Which is a fundamental misunderstanding of linguistics of how language works.
Yeah, to say nothing of theology and history and so forth.
Yes, that's not how language works.
Okay.
to determine how a particular author is using a word.
Yeah.
Right.
And that's what makes it even more stupid is that all of these are English translations
of these quotes.
Yeah.
It's not even the original words.
With people who probably are, yeah, exactly.
And often, in many cases, translated by Protestants and Catholics.
Yes.
You know, who are naturally going to use the terminology they're used to in their version
of English?
Right.
This is assuming that words, a word just means something.
Yeah, the sort of the matter who uses it when and where and there's another word in another language that is identical and interchangeable with it. Yeah, yeah, that's why I say this is a fundamental
lack of comprehension of the most basic aspects of how language works, right? Yeah, um
Send your hate mail to father Andrew
But because we point that out, we're modernists.
Yes, right.
You're a magisterial model.
our next father.
Yeah.
So, okay.
I do host the magisterial livestream for modernists.
That's true.
Okay.
So you mentioned, you mentioned narcissism earlier as something that needs to be brought up in
the midst of all this.
So what do you mean by that?
What's going on?
Right.
Because if you're looking for something Christian-ish that also looks like a mystery called,
narcissism is where you want to go.
Right?
You could really have it to leak class of initiates.
who have a kind of different religion based on religious experience than the broad range
of people, right?
You also have them perceiving there to be classes of people who are just incapable of religion,
right?
Or at least of their religion.
You have a whole series of cults with parallel mystery practices, the Valentinians, the
at the ends of the URLs.
And there's no sort of, like I said, you've got the levels of initiates and then, you know,
a whole bunch of people who are just cut out, right, in the same way with the mystery called
Sleik Slavs, not invited people, right, not invited.
So Nostasisism is closer.
And now for this evening's spicy tip.
not a lot of spice in the Thanksgiving food usually. Some people get a little
creative down here with the turkey. You get some seasoning on that turkey.
And my wife makes these amazing yams with crack and spice rum. Just marinate
the yams in it. But here's your flavor.
Let's talk about you.
Geicalism. This is my tribe, you know, we've been talking about, uh, not me more. Uh, yeah,
don't go a humanist on me here. Um, the, uh, uh, so we've been talking about historic Christianity.
Let's clarify when I say evangelicalism.
I do not mean all Protestantism, right?
So evangelicalism is not what we might call
classical Protestantism, right?
Your Lutherans, your Calvinists, right?
Evangelism is not liberal Protestantism,
like mainline liberal, you know,
your United Methodists, your PCUSA,
your Mike Lansman.
Um, my
like Mike Lansman?
Yes.
Yes, your Mike Lansman.
Yeah, no, it's me.
I most often encounter him in conjunction with you.
That is true.
Yeah, I mean, it's and it's it's it's this movement that came out of the second great
awakening, the holiness movement revivalism.
And also we're not even talking about British evangelicalism.
We're talking about American.
Yeah, yeah.
And and and just to further disambiguate.
Evangelicalism
as a religious movement and as the way that it works should be distinguished from particular
evangelicals who may have their own sets of behavior, their own way of doing things that's
not just simply exactly whatever it is the rest of this movement is doing.
Yes, we can hate this sin and love the sinter.
Here we go.
All right.
This is more hate the institution but love the people who are suffering from it.
Yeah.
I have never done it. I mean, I grew up evangelical.
Okay.
So I never ever doubted the sincerity of the people that I was with and their love for Jesus Christ never ever
It was very clear to me how much they love Jesus Christ and are trying to be faithful to him in the very very best way that they know how
You know
And I think that that yes that that and I believe I personally believe I'm not gonna dogmatically state
But I personally believe that God will have mercy on people and
An honor the love that they have for him
in whatever context.
that happens to be, that doesn't validate the context,
it doesn't make anything automatic or whatever,
but that God will judge people based on his knowledge
of everything about them.
Right, and this is not a compromise.
Right, this is not a sort of, like, so, like I said,
I just drew a contrast between Christianity
and evangelicalism. I did.
Okay.
Okay, I did that.
Right
So that does not mean, right?
So that means, I mean according to there for a certain definition,
as somebody's uncle may already be screaming,
if you did actually take my advice and play this,
drag your things, giving me a lot of the West Coast.
It's your own fault.
We told you not to.
It does mean for a certain person,
you could say, well, Father,
Stephen, you're saying that evangelicals aren't Christians.
Well, according to what definition they're not.
The court of the definition of members of Christ's Church, which is the Holy Orthodox Church,
they're not.
If your definition of Christian is person participating in historic Christianity, honestly, they're
not, right?
Now, if your definition is like the definition that Father Andrew just gave, if what you
mean by Christian is a person who loves Jesus as who they understand him to be and is
Spencer live doing
their best to follow Christ to the best of their ability and the best of their knowledge,
then yes, a lot of evangelicals are Christians by that definition.
Okay.
And none of those categorizations I just made have anything to do with who goes to hell.
Yeah.
Zero.
Zero relevant.
That's frankly.
None of the statements I made say that that's frankly that anybody is or isn't going
to hell.
That's frankly an evangelical assumption.
Yes.
But that gets read in.
Yeah.
That gets read it. So I have made zero statements thus far about anyone going to hell. Okay.
It's just how do you define this term and then does person X fit that definition or not?
So according to some definitions of Christian. Yes, other definitions of Christian. No, right?
And none of those definitions had anything to do with who goes to heaven and who goes to hell
Especially not who goes to heaven because you know the resurrection of the body and all that
But so what we're going to be talking about here is we've been talking about Christianity,
not about a group of Christians who are Christians according to a certain definition.
And we're going to be talking about that versus evangelicalism as a set of practices and a certain
type of ritual life.
even jocals have rituals, whether they want to call them that or not.
Right.
Um, they, they go to the same building on the same, at the same time, every Sunday, right,
and do roughly the same things.
Guess what?
That's a ritual.
Um,
right.
Uh, and that is nothing to do with whether the people there who are Christians under a certain definition,
we're not talking about that.
We're talking about the system of practices.
Right.
the practice, practice of
of this religious group versus the practice of this other religious group.
I'm labeling one as historic Christianity because if we're honest,
that's just what it is.
I accepted other groups.
Classical Protestants would say that what I'm calling historical Christianity
at some point historically departed from some key principles of Christianity.
So, and that's an argument we get at.
Okay, that does it is it germane here either
So I'm not saying
Anything about any person listening to this is eternal destiny or any of their family or friends
Eternal destiny. I'm saying nothing about that. I am not even really saying who isn't is in a Christian because that just depends on how you define Christian
I am kind of saying that a lot of these things that people call churches aren't really churches
So, just to cop to what I'm actually saying, be mad about what I'm actually saying, not
what I'm not saying.
So, evangelicalism and mystery cults.
As Father Andrew mentioned, when we're talking about American evangelicalism, we're really
talking about the movements that come out of the Second Great Awakening and the revival
movements of the mid-19th century.
Charles Finney at all.
Yeah.
Now, if we look at those and the practices and everything, are they oriented toward the
individual or toward the collective?
We kind of have to say individual.
Not just because of some kind of objective analysis forces us, but because evangelicals
insist upon it.
Yeah, absolutely.
Absolutely.
You don't exist upon it.
I can give you quotes, video and audio of evangelical leaders saying that any group that teaches
any form of collective salvation rather than individual salvation is not Christian.
Yeah, I mean, this is the idea that I was raised with.
Absolutely.
Yes.
I can confirm.
So it is about who and not.
They would say I'm not a Christian.
Yeah, it is but
your relationship with God. That is the thing that really, really matters is you and Jesus.
Right. Yeah. Right. And that is an individual thing. Right.
We would have to say, look at evangelicalism because this is what evangelicalism itself says
that experience, religious experience, is central.
Yeah.
You have to religious identity.
And the practice, we can see in the practice, the practice is aimed toward experience.
But think about the whole, it's not a religion, it's a relationship thing.
is treated in evangelicalism as both the purpose of the ritual.
So you're going and participating in it in order to have the experience to engender the experience and
having the experience is
what gives the ritual, what gives the practice its validity.
Meaning
you go to church in order to have the experience.
If you go to church and you don't have the experience
You
don't feel the spirit moving, right? Then that invalidates the church, the church
experience. You're either going to start looking for another church if that keeps
happening, right? Or you're going to change the practice of the church because
the church is now dead, right? Or if it's spiritual practice in your
personal life, right? You're whatever your prayer and devotional practices, just
you have a dry spell where it's not produced.
any kind of spiritual experience, you're going to change that practice up, right, to try to make that happen.
You get a lot of moving around from church to church because of that in the evangelical world.
Yeah, I'm not being fed.
Yeah, right. You get jumping from church to church and you go to the new place and the new place.
You start having the experiences again, but then it wears off so you move to the next one.
one.
This is one of the reasons why I'm so glad we have a one year waiting period on joining the orthodox church
Because we would have a lot more people hopping their way through otherwise
Yeah, we just signed up everybody who walked through the door the average day would be about six months three to six months and they'd be gone
Um
The right because
You're you're sort of chasing the experience the average Southern Baptist is baptized 2.0
seven times in their lifetime and they don't practice
infant baptism, so that's not one of them.
Because you don't have the experience or you continue to
experience a struggle with sin in your life, so maybe it didn't take.
Right, that's the validation.
You have this sort of broad evangelicalism.
right where you could basically be an evangelical Christian by just identifying as an evangelical Christian.
Right? Any politician could get up and say that. Right?
Yeah. Even if they were a Hindu last week, we've seen this recently.
They don't have to do anything. They don't have to. Right?
So there's this very broad thing. But then almost every evangelical group
The helical group.
has a class of elites. It depends where you're located in this sort of evangelical sphere
of who those elites are. So if you're more on the Stadiole Baptist side,
then your elites are people with doctor before their name.
Yeah. Seminary professors, guys who have published books, guys who are
doctor so and so. Right? If you're on the other end of evangelicalism, the like
charismatic pedicostle and then it's the charismatic spirit-filled, right,
leadership who may be doing miracles and stuff, right? That class of people, right?
Who everyone goes to receive prophecies and blessings and advice and and all of
of this sort of thing, that they have some kind of access to the holly.
spirit that the Huyploi don't have, same thing on the other side, but intellectually,
but in both of those cases, and critically, those elites are sort of the means through which
the spiritual experience that the general run of people can have is mediated.
Having the spirit filled guys show up at your revival.
is how your revival gets the spirit moving and everybody has the experiences.
Right? Yep. Or having the guy who's spent his life studying the Bible and preaching it
verse by verse, I really be more appreciated as a Baptist, I think. You would.
Show me just by J. Vernon McGee approach. That's right. To quote one of the spiritual elites
reference on the street.
That guy comes and really brings the word to you.
Yeah, he really brought it.
Goes it deep, right?
And produces this experience of people with, if you're really the Stodgy Baptist camp,
no outward manifestation whatsoever.
Because that may be the case you'll, during the sermon.
Depending on region, they're permitted some amends.
Yes, but reservedly
You don't go crazy with that.
Yeah.
Um, so, uh, and of course there's everybody in between, right, between those two extremes.
Um, but the dynamics are the same, right?
Uh, you definitely get, and I'm sorry for anyone this, sorry not sorry for anyone's bubble.
This is bursting, but you definitely get techniques used to produce altered states of consciousness.
I mean long repetitive praise cord is long periods of time
I'm standing on your feet.
Yeah.
I mean, literally now moving lights and fog machines.
I mean, this is...
Drowning.
Yeah, honestly, part of this is why I left that
because when I left, I was working as a stage hand
at the time and I knew very, very well
through the use of technique
that I could make people feel certain things.
Let's just all live about Dave.
Oh, you want me to tell everybody about Dave Matthews?
Tell everybody about Dave.
Yeah, okay, so I've told the story before.
I don't know if it's been on this podcast.
There was a summer where I saw Dave Matthews man three times
and it's not because, you know,
I just wanted to litter in or have her hold my hand.
But no, no, it was because I was working.
And hold my hand is hoody, dude.
Oh, right.
That's true.
Man, I'm just personally going to be a hoody free zone.
This is the last time I tell you to tell a story.
Who do you free zone? Can I have that as a muppers ticker?
It's funny, you know as I've aged I've gotten a little bit more who do you friendly which I don't know what's happening to be but
But anyway, we don't even know one jam band from another. I know I remember when who didn't blowfish was just like playing frat parties in South Carolina before they were a big deal
So anyway, it's true. So anyway
Yes, Dave Matthews been and so they always played and smarting.
That's one of course one of their big hits and there is at the same moment in the song
There was always a point where a big bank of lights that was facing the house that is to say the people rather than the stage
at that point in the song
those lights would all come on and illuminate the house and
At that point every single time I saw this thought I saw this three times in one year
Everybody out there.
out there goes crazy.
Like they have big excited feeling and, you know,
ah, you know, every time.
And I mean, what's inducing that?
Literally a guy like me was sitting in front
of a lighting control console and he pressed a button.
And when he pressed that button,
those people had that experience.
Now they probably wouldn't have identified it
as a spiritual experience,
but it was clearly an emotional experience
at the very least.
and let's face it.
Again, I'm speaking as someone who came from this group a
emotional experience in many cases
Equal spiritual experience for a lot of people there like when someone says
I really feel the spirit in the room tonight. What do they mean by that?
What is how do they know that what are our feeling? They're having is the Holy Spirit like where in the scripture
Does it say and you will feel the following and that should be identified as the presence of the Holy Spirit never says that
never says that
so yeah for me
this is part of why I left all that because not be
because I doubted the sincerity of the people involved,
not in the least, not from a minute.
But I knew that-
We'll look at the orchestrators.
Yeah.
But that I knew that I could make it happen
by with the professional skills
that I had learned working in theater.
You know? Yeah.
And this is not something that started out totally sincere
and now has become jaded, okay?
If you go and read Finney's on revival,
his magnum opus to Endal opus's magnum,
He says in there, so this is at the beginning of the evangelical revivalist movement.
He says in there that there is nothing supernatural about conversion.
Yeah, it can be achieved through technique.
Yes, it can be achieved through the application, consistent application of techniques.
People converting to Christ.
Right.
There's nothing supernatural about it.
There's that whole anxious bench, you know, like it's a technique.
Now, you know, I don't think that...
I mean, I don't know Charles Finney's heart,
the man's been dead for a long time.
But.
He was a rank heretic.
But, you know, yeah, I mean, sure, absolutely.
Right, but at the same time, like,
I mean, a modern evangelical worship team would say,
no, this is when we play the music this way
that makes it possible for people to experience the spirit
or something like that.
And they're doing it because they have that experience
performing.
Right, right, exactly.
Yeah.
So there's a lot of that.
There are guys way at the top who are the jaded ones.
The guys you've heard of, the big name guys, the guys who want your money.
And of course, especially when we get into the charismatic end of evangelicals,
there's a lot of ecstatic behavior where people sort of get riled up in the experience,
friends eating the experience of the point that you know.
things get a little nuts, right?
And so, got to kind of conclude,
there are some real problematic correspondences
between evangelicalism and mystery cults.
And that is primarily this aim of experience,
making experience the end in itself.
And the type of experience it is is always an experience that is ecstatic, stands outside,
an escape from reality, an escape from the material in created world.
And so we come back to an idea we first floated in the first half, which is that ritual normally
is about shaping how we experience and interact with real life.
with the created physical world at which we inhabit and the spiritual world, which we also inhabit.
So shaping that. Whereas the pursuit of experience is pretty much always rooted in running away from that.
Yeah. Right. No one going to be initiated in the Dionysian mysteries. Right. Thought that had some
application to their job as a Roman senator when they went back to Rome.
Right, it was this extreme spiritual experience away from all that, right?
Abstracted from all that.
Well, this has been one of our wilder episodes, I think, especially in terms of the specific
content we've discussed.
But I think that, you know, you mentioned a number of times Christianity isn't...
antithesis to these mystery cults.
And there's two things I want to say about that.
I mean, number one, I think the more clearly you see the ancient world for what it really
was, the more clearly we can see the love of God for us in coming here as one of us to
rescue us from that.
from that. Yeah, that's my first thought about that. And then the second thought is that
the motivation for mystery cults still exists. It still exists. We're always looking for
some other form of salvation or exaltation or enlightenment or whatever it might be.
And some people think that you can get that through
education.
Some think that you can get that, whether that's, you know, formal or, you know, self-taught.
Some people think you can get that through using a particular
drug, you know,
or a particular practice.
You know, there's always some kind of silver bullet. Some thing that you do, or that you go through.
or that you achieve.
And then, and then, then you will arrive.
Then you'll get there.
Then you'll be, you know, what it is you want to be.
And, of course, a lot of this is being done
as alternatives to Christianity.
People want to go through this other thing
and that's going to be the thing that we'll get them there, you know.
But there are people who treat Christianity this way
or what they think Christianity is.
You know, and I see this even within the Orthodox Church, sometimes people will pinpoint a particular thing.
You need to do this or you need to say this or you know, whatever shibboleth they have in mind or whatever,
whatever thing that is the switch that needs to be flipped.
And then on the other side of that, you're higher, you're better, you're, you've arrived, you know, whatever it might be.
But that's not the way the Christianity works.
The Lord told us that in this world we would have trouble.
And it's easy to take pot shots at like word faith, Pentecostos who say, you know, do the
following thing and you will have health, you will have wealth, you will have whatever
it is.
God wants to be good to you all the time.
you're just blocking it because you're not saying the right thing.
because you're not affirming the right things.
Right?
This is clearly another technique like this, you know?
That's easy to kind of point out and say how wrong that is.
What's the bit?
Why do people want that?
I think they want it because they're trying to escape the suffering of this world, the
trying to escape whether it's physical suffering,
financial suffering.
psychological suffering, dealing with the ambiguity of this world, dealing with the fact
that other people sin, dealing with the fact that I sin, if only I did this, if only whatever,
right? It's always the if only, some solution. The evil of this world does not have a solution.
Then Christ of course came to destroy evil.
But he didn't come to give us a fix.
He came to give us a way of faithfulness that if we walk it, if we stay faithful to it,
if we are loyal to him, if we get up every time that we fall and maintain that, then that
way will gradually transform us to be the people that he created us to be.
There is no shortcut to knowledge, there is no shortcut to exaltation.
There's no shortcut to salvation.
There's no shortcut to enlightenment.
There's no experience that you can go through
that is gonna turn you into a saint.
There's no experience you can go through
that's gonna transform your family around you.
No, it's faithfulness.
It's gradual.
It's work.
It's day in, day out.
I think it's this desire for fixes
that is the reason why so many people,
even sometimes entering to your Orthodox church,
can come in and then they flare up, they blaze so bright, so glorious, and then they burn out.
It's because they're not actually doing the day-in-day out faithfulness in community
with the church.
Mystery cults promised an underground passage that you could go through, do weird,
deeply disturbing stuff down there in the dark and you would come out a different.
person. But it's not Christianity. Christianity echoing the words of her
Lord says in this world you will have trouble. And this world you're going to
be persecuted. And this world is going to be difficult. And most of the trouble,
at least for those of us in the comfortable West, the most of the trouble that
we experience is not other people doing it to us. It's the experience that we
have of being sinners. It's something that in many cases we're doing to ourselves.
I'm not saying other people are not harming you.
They certainly are. But most of the struggle that we have is a struggle against our own
sins. So yeah, I mean, I get the appeal of escape. I've tried a lot of things. I figured
if I just, if I go through this, if I flip this switch, if I do that, then, then, you
know, but there's no shortcuts. And the reason why we experienced the suffering of
life that we do is because God knows that this is what we need to be saved. And to be saved
means to become sons of the resurrection, sons of God equal to the angels. As Jesus said,
that's what it means. It's through this faithfulness that we are saved, it is through this
faithfulness that we receive the gift of God that transforms us into being the saints
that he...
created us to be.
And so I think that this exploration of this weird dark messed up subject
and looking at its echoes in the modern world as uncomfortable as that might be.
I think that it helps us to see what it means to be Christian,
helps us to understand better the way that we should go.
and I hope gives us some encouragement for the way.
as we take this pilgrimage through life.
So those are my thoughts about all this.
So yeah, I always assume that pretty much everybody listening to this podcast
is not a monastic that they're living in the world.
If you are a man...
listening to this podcast. Why? That's what I think. Why are you on the internet for three hours at a time?
And why this episode of all episodes? Exactly. We do, I will say we I am aware of at least a couple that
listen. So hello. Yeah. Hello. So it's great for us. So yeah, if you've made it this far.
But that's not most of our audience.
Save very-
safely. That's not most of our audience. And one of the problems I think that's still
lingers around, at least in American orthodoxy, a lot, is, again, we talked about that tendency,
fundamentalist tendency and I don't think it goes quite that far but
There's a little flavor of, well, the monastics are sort of the real Orthodox Christians, right?
They're the spiritual elite class and we're, you know, the Hoy-Poleu.
As if monasticism is a calling, and if you're not called to that, you're not called to anything in particular.
You're just sort of, yeah.
Right?
Oh, I'm just a lay person in the world, right?
rather than understanding that we're called precisely to the world.
That is an actual positive calling to live your life in the world.
And it is the most common calling.
It is far more common than the calling to monasticism.
That's a good thing.
It is the calling that Adam and Eve received,
who were not called to monasticism or there would be no
people. They were called to what? We've talked about this on the show before. Fill the
earth and subdue it. Go out into the world, fill the world with life, and put it in order.
And one bit of feedback that I've actually read and spent a lot of time thinking about,
the fact that was
And we've talked about this before on the show,
and what it means to be active in the world's
Christians and talking about this calling,
fill the world of life and put it in order.
We've talked about how men really major in the putting
in order side and participate in the filling with life.
And women sort of major in the filling with life and
participate in the putting in order is that a lot of our
women listeners.
feel that that's kind of vague on their side.
That we have a lot more clarity about the male side than the female side.
Part of that is because Father Andrew and I are men and not women.
So we don't know what it's like to be a woman.
And so being men, we're just sort of naturally more intuitively familiar with that side.
So we understand that...
masculine side of engagement with the world with the actual real material world we live in on a day to day basis.
Right. We understand those aspects, the idea that you put up fences, the idea that you defend. Right. You part of putting in where you defend what is holy, what is good, what is pure.
from what isn't, right? You separate those, you defend it. Sometimes you even have to
attack a little and drive off potential threats and invaders.
Right?
That whole aspect that whole masculine aspect of priesthood and stuff where men were priests
We get that we understand it so
The rest of this and particularly because of our topic tonight ironically since I don't know how many of our female listeners made it this far
But this one's for the ladies
Because I've been thinking more and more about this what does it mean?
beyond the object.
of biological reproduction that women major in and their role is filling the world with life.
And the reason I think about it in this context of our episode tonight with all of its grossness is because
what we were talking about tonight in this way of antithesis with the mystery cults is a flight from reality
a flight from the world and seeking an escape from the world.
And this is supposed to engagement with the world.
So let me be very concrete.
What I think it means for women as women to fill their world with life,
means that while men are protecting the fences and creating this space within that space,
women are finding what is good, what is beautiful, what is pure and what is wonderful.
about the world we
live in and the people in it. All of the people in it, every person in it. And every created
thing has something about it that is beautiful and that is pure and that is noble. When St.
Paul says, whatever is good and pure in noble, think on these things, he's not talking about
the platonic forms and contemplation. He's talking about the actual world that God created
and called good. And he's talking about every person in it, no matter how far they fall
want in to sit. Whatever is good.
and noble and pure and beautiful about them.
I think this is the concreteness of how a woman nurtures and fills the world with life,
is looking at everything and every person, finding those things,
the goodness, that purity, that beauty,
and nurturing it and cultivating it,
and helping bring it forth.
Right?
while men are mining the borders, right, in the fences and keeping the threats out.
That then as makes women free to do that and safe to do that.
And that is in our modern world, which is very ugly in a lot of ways. We all see the
ugliness.
the time. We all see what is dishonorable, we all see what is impure, we all see what is
ignoble in our present world. And in which frankly a lot of we've talked before it meant abandoning
their jobs. A lot of women have abandoned their jobs too because a lot of them have decided they
like the man's job better and they want to do that.
Right? It is vitally important.
For people to be able to live Christian lives or any kind of life in the world, that there
is someone who is finding the good and the pure and the beautiful and bringing it forth
and nurturing it and fanning the sparks and the flames, right, to bring that out and
and help it grow and help each of us grow.
Right.
not just within the church community, but within the broader culture, within the broader society.
Right? Because, you know, men may be great at fighting off the ugly and defeating the evil and putting these things down.
But things also need to get built up and grow.
And these things need to be brought out.
So I hope in terms of some past episodes that gives a
little more clarity. I'm actually hoping next time we do a Q&A and I don't know
when that'll be, but the next time we do one, maybe we'll some of our female
collars will call and interact with us about that. But I also think that in the
face of various forms which
You know, hey, I argue even evangelicalism is basically one of the re-emergence of this
ecstatic
mystery cult idea of
spiritual experience removing us from this world. This world is so ugly and terrible. I must escape it. I must get away from it
To some other place that in the face of that
We bring forth we bring forth the opposite and
And in this case, I think women have a critically important role to play that can't be neglected
and can't be overappreciated when it happens.
Amen.
Well, that's our show for tonight.
Thank you very much for listening.
This pre-recorded Thanksgiving episode.
We didn't take calls this time, but you can still email us at LordofSpiritsNationFace.com.
You can message us to our Facebook page.
You can also leave us a voice mail.
speak pipe
dot com slash Lord of Spirits and if you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity
or you need help to find a parish, go to Orthodox intro dot org.
And join us for our live broadcast on the second four Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m.
Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
You come out at night.
That's when the energy comes and the dark side's light and the vampires roam.
If you're on Facebook, you can follow our page.
Join us in this question group there.
reviews ratings every
Everywhere because that builds a mystery.
Most importantly, those share this show with a friend who is going to benefit from it.
And finally be sure to go to AncientFate.com, Stroke Support, and help make sure we and lots
of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
You live in a church where you sleep with voodoo dolls.
You won't give up the search for the ghosts and the halls.
Thank you.
Good night and God bless you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox...
Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener-supported
presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches
and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.